<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Management | Oliver Thylmann]]></title>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/categories/management/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-10T11:31:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://thylmann.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oliver Thylmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Human Resource dimensions of innovation and knowledge management]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/03/07/the-human-resource-dimensions-of-innovation-and-knowledge-management/"/>
    <updated>2005-03-07T21:12:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/03/07/the-human-resource-dimensions-of-innovation-and-knowledge-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;(comment: As originally posted on the OUBS Blog)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This unit is about the two dimensions of the resource of knowledge workers and the management of the process for innovation. Remember that not all knowledge workers need to be innovative. But also, knowledge might be necessary but not enough to manage human resources for innovation. The efficient management of information is still under-used, managed and attached importance to. Managements role is then about facilitation, nurturing, supporting, ...&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knowledge Work: A conceptual framework&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;For one remember that each initiative has to be seen in context, meaning that for example a command/control culture will likely not foster knowledge sharing. Is everyone a knowledge worker or only those not working on non-material things, and does this maybe just simply relabels them? Is that relabeling just a fad, even if knowledge is not? Maybe our move to service work has made knowledge more central. Actually, anything that can be automated will, and hence information and knowledge, or rather knowing, is key. Is the knowing worker, the worker of the future?&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In a sense, this means that future companies might be more knowledge than capital intensive and then people need to be managed differently, as they hold your success in their heads. It is no more about access to capital but to knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;What do these knowledge workers contribute? Human assets are part of the intangible asset pool of a company, but they do not belong to the company. They should be management like finances are and in this case the &quot;resources&quot; can actually also be found outside the company. You need to facilitate, coach, empower, foster lifelong learning, knowledge capture and sharing, motivation and commitment.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In the industrial age the focus was on division of labor and the &quot;one best way&quot;, rules objectivity, technology, ... But this knowledge age depends on factors that are not heightened by rules or objectivity. They need the above traits like intuition and commitment. Managers were bosses giving orders, held responsible and knowing everything. Now this is harder as you can't know everything in a knowledge economy and hence the manager has become a coach, working on moving intellectual capital from people to the organization or actually just between people, working on making them stay. The idea that you need to move knowledge to the company is actually just the easy version of all of this, not taking into account that you might not be able to in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Organizational forms are also being changed from hierarchical to more distributed and blurry, with lateral information flows, often across boundaries needed new human resource ideas. If knowledge intensiveness is true, loosening of control and autonomy will be needed.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem of Managing knowledge Workers and &quot;Managing Innovation&quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Innovator companies are characterized as including visionaries, open cultures, market focussed staff and are open to prototyping. This is far from easy:
- how do you access tacit knowledge and not instruct or control people from above?
- how to you gain trust, commitment and motivation?
- how do you deal with contrary legacy messages?
- how to you contract workers and consultants from the outside?
- how to you manage the vulnerability of the organization?
- how do you manage professional workers who seem to be harder to manage the more specialized they are?&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In terms of best practices there seem to be more poor than good examples for management of innovation. There are a lot of different views within one company about what innovation really is and without understanding this context, introducing aids to innovation is fruitless. The OUBS &quot;perceptions of innovation&quot; study revealed some barriers to innovation:
- silo mentality
- blame culture
- risk/reward
- bureaucracy
- poor communications
- short-termism, ROI focus&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HRM practices for knowledge work and innovation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A clear knowledge management focus in hr does need a different strategy than one focusses on cost. In this unit HR strategy is about structural and cultural strategy as well as HR practices. This links in directly with Gary Hamel's resource-based view on strategy and organizational capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organizational structures and enabling conditions
While structures are mostly linked to a command-control system, Nonaka and Takeuchi showed that given &quot;requisite variety&quot; structures can also help innovation, as this diversity needs to reflect market complexity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&quot;To maximize variety everyone in the organization should be assured of the fastest access to the broadest variety of necessary information, going through the fewest steps.&quot; - Nonaka and Takeuchi, 1995&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You could:
- Keep multiple links between diverse teams
- change structures frequently
- promote job rotation
- &quot;non-experts&quot; in new product-dev to challenge &quot;givens&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teams: shared context, open discussions, big pool of knowledge, big Ts
You need independent knowledge bubbles within structure with extensive links. Virtual teams are possible through ICT, allowing for dispersed COP to build.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You also need to foster collaboration instead of stars (or both) to improve better and more sustainable innovation. The team leader that becomes more of a coach, managing the discussion and collaboration, ... the team development, which today is really an HR function. We all need to become HR managers in a sense.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The spider's web organizational form is an idea to let the right teams form at the right time and place (also virtual). Mature teams, with possibility for individuality, clear goals, good sharing and the right resources seem to work best.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organization wide structures
Either you have an expert R&amp;D system or more of a collaborative innovation whole. R&amp;D needs interfaces to the business side obviously in both directions to allow market-pull and technology-push. Organization wide innovation in light of customer demands moves everything from asset management to resource leverage with wide information sharing. You should actually call the human resource manager the human asset leverager.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Joint problem solving and flexible specialization are often cited as important. Some big companies work towards this by subdividing when reaching a certain size. Even though flexibility is important you still seem to be able to use a bureaucratic system to foster flexibility. I think it's Stevel Ballmer from Microsoft who said that speed is not about being big or small, if you don't move, you don't move.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inter-organizational arrangements and networks
You need boundary spanners, that stay up to date on the latest happenings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Encouraging an appropriate culture is said to be key to performance. Some believe that culture can be managed. In relation to innovation this means managing failure, but in general this is how management behaves in reality (doing versus saying) that forms the culture. Conformance to to procedures and short-term profit focus are things noted as barriers to innovation.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Innovation can flourish based on Pascale (91) where:
- constructive criticism is welcome
- creative tension the norm
- curiosity
- passion for learning
- quality enhancement
- autonomy and independence
- free flow of innovation
-- few hierarchies
-- big cross boundary and cross functional focus
- bureaucracy -&gt; entrepreneurship (or intrapreneurship)
- everybody is a thinker (lean production)
- not cutting funding in crisis
- sharing knowledge (emphasized through performance evaluation and compensation)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Resourcing: Recruiting and selecting&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Peters and Waterman (82) argue that those closest to the customers are those most ripe for innovation. Diversity is given emphasis to foster alternative views. Peters (89) believes you need to seperate those using procedures and those breaking them, but others (Davenport, 93) argue that this is getting harder.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Your best people will likely be found by competitors and you need to use things like profit-sharing, challenge, environment and freedom to make them stay.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Leonard (98) suggests key themes in relation to learning, knowledge and innovation:
- shared problem solving
- experimentation and prototyping
- implementing new technical procedures and tools
- importing and absorbing from the outside
- learning from the market&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;All this need continuous learning on fertile ground. Top management needs to be sure that they don't kill of new ways the team is working, killing of their learning and sending a bad signal.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&quot;Knowledge is experience. Everything else is information.&quot; - Albert Einstein&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes knowledge stores actually become information junkyards (McDermott, 99) The structure of organizational memory beased on Walsh and Ungson (91) has several stores: See Figure 4.2.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;HR Managers need to enhance and exploit each of those. Stories and learning histories might be a good idea here which is where Blogs fit very well.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training for Creativity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;First you need the environment and then you need to test your people and develop them in the right direction. Competence modeling allows you to find those competences that you need and develop them (see activity 4.7)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The learning organization can proceed the knowledge company or vice versa, which depends on the viewpoint. But they are interlinked. Corporate universities show that the idea/need for both is growing, sometimes as a partnership with universities. There are different hierarchies of learning for example adapted by Quinn et. al.:
- know what
- know how
- know why
- care why&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;(one might argue that &quot;know who&quot; is another one if you can't know everything ;))&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Career development and management development is often linked to job rotation in successful cases, with managers being a core target group due to their industry knowledge. Courses, mentoring and coaching are other things that have been done successfully. Japan is strong in this respect and it shows in their knowledge increases.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;If you focus on management as a whole you really move from manager to management development. All the moves in that direction show the importance seen in KM and high-order learning.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Involving and Empowerment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;It's regarded as an alternative to command-and-control but there is little research on how to really make it work. It's about high-trust and high-commitment really. Wilkonson (98) has classified various types:
- information sharing
- upward problem solving (quality circles, ...)
- task autonomy
- attitudinal shaping
- self-management&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Success is dependent on context, and needs to move beyond delegating responsibility.  Without training, cost/reward and consistence it is futile.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Harnessing motivation: Performance management and rewards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;People, above all, need to be willing to share their knowledge. Hence you need job security, also be &quot;upgrading&quot; your employees to remain employable. Pay attention to:
- what gets measured gets done
- sharing needs to be rewarded (expertise networks are an idea)
- include km in routines (e.g. knowledge gained in project management)
- ict tools need to be appealing and useful&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;People need to feel they get more than they give. Amabile (98) identified 6 ingredients necessary:
- challenge
- freedom
- resources
- work-group feature
- supervisory encouragement
- organizational support&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A broader goal base seems to be needed and enjoying work important. The psychological contract need to make people investors.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HR strategies in context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You need to not work on one lever but on their balance and include a sociopolitical angle. Strategic integration is about your strategy being mutually reinforcing and Schuler and Jackson say these patterns are needed:
- high degree of creative behavior
- long-term focus
- co-operation
- moderate concern for quality
- moderate concern for output quantity
- risk taking
- high tolerance for ambiguity&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You need to find your best fit in this and it needs to result in a competitive advantage for all this to make any sense. This comes from: innovation, low cost or superior quality. You need to find the &quot;needed role behavior&quot; in relation to this and the fitting HR strategy. Innovation strategy does not require to work harder or smarter but differently by the way. You need to be sure to choose and match internal and external views.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You can also choose different types of innovation and then match different HR strategies. HR needs to fit to your organizations need. Managers need to use the right methods for the context to drive innovation. All this likely need to be changing over time too.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The sociopolitical context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Davenport argued, interestingly, that if there is not politics, then there seems to be no perceived value in knowledge. In any case the value is socially constructed, and not a given. Also it seems that employees actually are becoming less happy in their work and less secure in their job, making you wonder if all this is really gaining some traction or not. Then again, maybe this is just about competition. You still need to remember all the Es.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Knowledge and Innovation]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/02/27/managing-knowledge-and-innovation/"/>
    <updated>2005-02-27T19:04:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/02/27/managing-knowledge-and-innovation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;(comment: As originally posted on the OUBS Blog)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Nonaka and Takeuchi put it like this: knowledge creation -&gt; continuous innovation -&gt; competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Simple. You can also say that next to creation of knowledge you have application, transformation and integration and all those functions interact.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In the 17th century Francis Bacon saw economic power in scientific knowledge and the possibility to then control the world we live in. Peter Drucker stressed the importance of knowledge as a crucial economic resource in 1969 (The Age of Discontinuity). Many companies now see themselves as knowledge based.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;While knowledge creation leads to innovation it can also be argued that innovation leads to new knowledge, making this a circular process. Sometimes this process is needed to survive. Schumpeter actually pointed out that a main driver of innovation is the threat of innovation in your sector that you are missing. You need to learn to unlearn to learn again. Schumpeter's gales of creative construction or discruptive technologies can be mentioned here. You will need to create new knowledge internally and raise your awareness to external threats. On a macro economic level variety occurs higher than at the individual level, meaning you cannot do anything against it at this level.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition of innovation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This is about the new, both technological and organizational. Invention is only a building block and often does not have the economic benefit needed for sustained innovation. Drucker said systemic innovation is the &quot;purposeful and organized search for changes.&quot; You need to understand the technical and the organizational part of innovation to really manage it successfully. While innovation is often seen as a leap to something new, this includes a lot of small steps that led you there and will take you further, with the leap actually mostly being on impact. Radical innovation is a lot more risky, especially because once undertaken, there is probably not pool of knowledge to use to build it up.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embodied and embedded knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This is based on Blackler's list of <a href="http://owt.typepad.com/oubs/2005/01/managing_knowle.html">types of knowledge</a>. You can also say that &quot;innovation embodies knowledge, or that innovations have knowledge embedded in them.&quot; This is important considering worker education, especially in relation to some kinds of knowledge types only available in people, context, verbal communication or interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scientific and other knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;While it is often believed that technological innovation is the application of scientific knowledge, there are other types too even though. Still, the commercial application of scientific knowledge is a big field not to be underestimated, especially as it's creation relies on the application of human and financial resources, precluding some form of commercialism in science. In terms of commercial relevance you need to also include the education and training part of science, which will lead to new, potentially commercial, advances. In the end, a lot of different types of knowledge need to be integrated for innovation to be successful. Page 25 in the book does list some types of knowledge needed there and can be really helpful, also in terms of thinking about outsourcing.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knowledge creation and innovation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly little has been done to research knowledge management in relation to its agreed importance and research in other core functions.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Design, something that cannot be automated or routinized, can be closely related to Gibbons' Mode 2 knowledge or Flick's contingent knowledge or Schön's reflective practitioner. Schön actually sees design as a &quot;reflective conversation with the materials of the situation.&quot; Each problem is unique and handled in context. Some see it as a rational solving process but Dorst and Dijkhuis actually found out that each approaches appropriateness depends on the context.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This leads in to two perspectives on knowledge creation frameworks. In Nonaka's SECI model new knowledge comes from the interaction of implicit and explicit knowledge. Knowledge conversion is key and different types of knowledge are created at each step. (More on Nonaka <a href="http://owt.typepad.com/oubs/2005/01/managing_knowle.html">here</a>.)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Building a new product needs interaction from a lot of different people and both socialization and externalization, individuals from the ba of the team who form the ba of the organization. (Lots of ba in SECI ;))&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Top management needs to build a vision that shows the direction this knowledge creation should take. Then you have two dimensions of knowledge creation:
- epistomological dimensions: tacit/explicit conversion
- ontological dimension: individual to group to organization&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Cook and Brown emphasize the concept of knowing, which only really works in a master and apprentice system where you learn what knowing something really means.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Important here is that you need to have variety and a deep (beyond immediate need) knowledge pool and interaction and communication between different/diverse people.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Experimentation and prototyping is another way to innovate and its actually easy to do with today's technology in some fields. Leonard-Barton talks about it in her book &lt;em&gt;Wellsprings of Knowledge&lt;/em&gt; in terms of &quot;purposeful experimentation.&quot; You need to support risk taking and allow experimentation with the option of failure.  You need to put a system in place that allows all this to happen and foster learning from it. Unsuccessfully trying some things might lead to something successful in an unexpected field, something she calls &quot;failing forward.&quot; Rapid prototyping and an open mind is needed. Local experts, early adapter types and all the stuff from Malcolm Gladwell's Tipping Point is needed.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Thomke has found 4 main areas of focus to exploit technology with prototyping and experimentation in mind.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organize for rapid experimentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fail early and often, but avoid mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anticipate and exploit early information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combine new and traditional technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning and Innovation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Learning and knowledge creation are un-separable. Ruggles (1997) argues knowledge management needs 4 independent activities:
- knowledge identification
- knowledge codification
- knowledge interchange
- knowledge creation
(all this seems very similar to SECI)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A lot of firms need to go to learning by doing as Arrow (1962) believed, citing as evidence increased output. Ludvall talked about learning as incremental additions and deletions from your pool of knowledge through experience and practice. Cultural, social and historical as well as your own pool of knowledge interact. Everything is context sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knowledge Practices for Innovation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Either knowledge has its own dynamic or it is driven economically... technological push vs. market driven. Actually we are somewhere in the continuum between the two. We can actually build a matrix putting knowledge about means and about ends in categories of unknown, definable or understood.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;At a firm level your knowledge will be cumulative and path dependent and you need to balance keep your core constant and keep an eye on the edges, which should be fluctuating. Creative abrasion is a term signifying that different specialists share knowledge, like designers and coders, building new knowledge based on their different knowledge and viewpoints in the process.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategic Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You need to innovate to stay competitive and therefor build up the capability to do so strategically. But rational planning processes are rarely possible, so you need a way to manage and to cope with complexity. You need to continuously link opportunities to market possibilities, within and outside the organization.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Freeman (1992) identifies 6 strategies:
- Offensive innovation strategy
- Defensive innovation strategy
- Imitative innovation strategy
- dependent strategy (subcontractors and suppliers innovate)
- traditional products
- opportunist (identify niches)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perceptions of innovation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The extremes, found in a OUBS research by Storey (200), are routinized innovation versus more individual creative events. Most are in the middle. Different dimensions play a larger or smaller role dependent on who you ask. There is a social - individual dimension and the external - internal dimension.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Some things are noticeable in relation to this:
- innovation happens in stages, with potential reviews at each stage
- the social part emphasizes the influencing process part, or even fight for resources
- cross-functional teams are important
- skunkworks (Tom Peters), aka individual experimentation
- find and keep innovative individuals
- importance of inter-firm collaboration
- social relationships are critical (internal and external)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal and External Knowledge for Innovation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You need to build knowledge but also look for diversity which is sometimes found outside your organization. Make or buy is an important consideration here. Working internally has high costs and risks, while externalizing things means you need to work hard to select the right collaborators. Learning from consultants needs a real effort as they are often not there to part with their specialized knowledge. The capability you can build is choosing, communicating and taking advantage of external resources. Outsourcing can be related to more diversity and larger communities of practice, which actually makes it attractive if the right partners are chosen.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In terms of R&amp;D it can be argued that the capability to orchestrate resources needs to be internal but the build does not need to be. Remember the transaction costs though.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brands]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/02/11/brands/"/>
    <updated>2005-02-11T20:56:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/02/11/brands</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;(comment: As originally posted on the OUBS Blog)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&quot;In the future the brand will be the most important asset of the firm.&quot; - Jean Noel Kapferer (1992)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Brands can take many forms, from FMCG to pop stars and places. They make the ware stand out in functional performance and psycho-social emotions. The ware is augmented, featuring tangible and intangible assets. When these are unique and relevant they can have a powerful influence on customer's choice.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;As brands are a lot less easy to copy, the provide a lot of strategic value to companies. Good brands lead to potential for premium prices, more bargaining power in the value chain and more customer loyalty. Brands help leverage resources and makes them unique, very important in the resource based view of strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are different forms of knowledge needed for managing a brand.
&lt;img width=&quot;512&quot; vspace=&quot;4&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; height=&quot;253&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; alt=&quot;Brand-Knowledge&quot; src=&quot;http://owt.typepad.com/oubs/images/Brand-Knowledge.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This does show the idea that brand management is about applied knowledge management. You need to manage knowledge at the:
- customer level: needs, wants, ... knowing and exceeding them
- intra-organizational level: understanding and consensus among staff about the brand
- inter-organizational level: all stakeholders that have influence on the brand&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Then there is the customer level: You cannot control but influence how customers make sense of your messages. Using communication and ICT is key here. There are several levels of communication:&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traditional Communication: Change attitudes through planned messages. Assumes a passive recipient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrated Communication: controlling and coordinating multiple flows of information; more personalized messages; does not believe in shared attitudes of all customers; critical recipient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value Added Communication: Coordinating multiple sources and giving the customers information when, where and how they choose to want it; interactive communication; building relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Distributors often know a lot more about the customer than manufacturers, but they might be willing to share that EPOS and loyalty card data. Consumer to consumer interaction is also rising, moving the power back to the individual. It goes as far as the buyer becoming the advertiser by announcing  their will to buy (Schultz 1996)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A company needs to understand the purchase decision process and be available at the right steps. Managing the brand internally is important as brands can be linked to living entities who start their lives internally. Employees that know the brand value are more likely to deliver that value externally. If you want to be seen as innovative you need to foster an innovative spirit internally. Everybody needs to know and feel that in advance of outside communication.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;All this then needs to be extended to other (external) stakeholders that the company might interact with, meaning that you need shared knowledge and communication channel going over the corporate boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Knowledge and Brand Creation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;It's about communication, functional and emotional. Strong relationships build on:
- honesty
- trustworthiness
- reliability
- predictability&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You need to understand the beliefs and value systems of the company. &quot;Information becomes knowledge when it is interpreted [...] 'truth', 'goodness' and 'beauty' are in the eye of the beholder.&quot; - Nonaka et al.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Nonaka's SECI Model can be helpful here as brand knowledge is just a special form of knowledge. Based on epistemological pluralism there are a lot of ways to know things and all facets play a role in brand knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A brand can be seen as:
- a legal instrument
- a logo (but it is not something to do to consumers but something they do things with)
- a company (gives a coherent focus)
- an identity (making the brand explicit)
here you look at the brand's values, create a vision from that and then move to a graphical representation of that vision. Kapferer believes good brand management begins with a &quot;strategy and consistent, integrated vision.&quot; This then gets translated into everything the consumer interacts with.
- an image in consumers' minds (facing the challenge of consumers' perception)
- as a personality to go beyond copyable functional advantages
- as a relationship to further extend the personification
- as a cluster of values&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing knowledge in different brand contexts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;So we need to manage different kinds of knowledge at three levels. But now we look at the different contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A: Consumer Brands&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Consumers go through similar decision processes all the time and brands help them in their search and evaluation work. For one there is the topology of the buying process:&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extended problem solving happens when there is high consumer involvement and significant perceived brand difference. You move through: Problem recognition -&gt; Information Search -&gt; Evaluation of alternatives -&gt; Purchase -&gt; Post purchase evaluation (Solomon et al. 1999)
With these kind of products consumers likely use a lot of different channels and you need to make sure that you are presenting a consistent message over all those channels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dissonance reduction is needed with high involvement but little brand difference. Advice by friends or others gain more importance and people are generally unsure of their purchase after the fact. This leads to the following process: Problem recognition -&gt; Purchase decision made -&gt; Brands then evaluated -&gt; Brand beliefs formed by active learning and information search&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In this case you need brand re-assurers reducing the perceived risk of choosing the wrong thing.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limited problem solving no matter what the involvement means that the cost of information search and evaluation is seen as too high. You go through the following process: Problem recognition -&gt; Brand beliefs formed from passive learning recalled from memory -&gt; Purchase made -&gt; Brands may or may not be evaluated afterwards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Here you need to make sure that your brand is in stock at the POS, keep things simple and keep the brand at the top of the consumer's head through advertising.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the idea of brand loyalty; meaning that consumers remove the effort of search and evaluation by sticking to one brand. You need to understand the consumer and try to get into their repertoire of brands. A relationship helps here and all staff need to be aware of this and the importance of a consistent communication of build the brand.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This also means a company cannot misuse the information at there disposal in relation to consumers needs and wants. Consumers need to feel that they get value for the information they gave.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;B: B2B Brands&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In B2B markets the specification between brands will be similar but some can maintain a higher market share and premium prices, which is linked to the perception of superior value. You need to look at the multiple facts that provide value to the perceiver/customer. The value to the customer depends on the transaction as a whole, shown through the pinwheel of brand value (Mudambi et al, 1997). It has several different facets:&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Product performance:
- Tangible: Fit, Defects
- Intangible: Reliable, highly technological&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Distribution performance:
- Tangible: lead time, JIT, online ordering
- Intangible: reliable, hassle free&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Support Services performance
- Tangible: range of services
- Intangible: expertise, rapport&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Company performance (as a whole):
- Tangible: profitability, market share
- Intangible: Reputation, image&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The most successful B2B brands have a well balanced pinwheel.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You can enhance the value of your brand through building relationships with others. This is most favorable if there is little risk involved but a potential high value added in terms of brand value transfer. While the functional capabilities might fit you should also look at the emotional values. Here you can look at Schein's three layers manifesting culture and values:
- artefacts
- values
- basic assumptions (mental models)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;C: Service Brands&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Service brands are more based on the intra-organizational level because they rely more on people. You need to focus on knowledge management to deliver consistent high level of service. There are several distinctive characteristics:
- Inseparability of production and consumption (you need to try to keep employees on one level, but obviously not at the lowest)
- Intangibility, meaning difficulty of sharpness of differentiation (difficult to judge QOS before the fact)
- Heterogeneity. They are difficult to standardize and might even have to be variable on a per customer basis. You need to build up a tacit knowledge and reinforce that internally.
- Perishability as it cannot be stored&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;To execute the service brand strategy you need to remember that employees pay a larger role and open communication is needed to pull together all employees, making sure their efforts result in customer satisfaction and increased sales, which then feeds back to motivation through a job well done.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brand Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You might need to know what your brands is worth. First you should look at the stages in your customer decision processes and evaluate how much value is created for you through your brand at each step.
- Awareness: familiarity and unaided recall are measures here
- Perception and Attitudes: here different attributes are ranked via different brands
- Preference: What brand do you prefer, x or y?
- Choice of intentions: Do you prefer but do not need the brand? It might be the best ice cream but it still doesn't sell as you don't want ice.
- Actual choice&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Why should you evaluate brand value though?
- To buy or sell a brand
- To measure brand management effectiveness
- To determine the appropriate level of future brand support.
- To make financial forecasts
- To identify underlying sources of brand value&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Methods of measuring brands can be:
- price premium (focussed on the past)
- market share
- a combined price premium and market share, looking at the rise of the curve seeing how much your market share drops with increases in price. The steeper the better.
- proprietary measures&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intellectual Capital]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/01/17/intellectual-capital/"/>
    <updated>2005-01-17T20:55:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/01/17/intellectual-capital</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of stories showing that the right measurement is important, that market valuation is not a simple calculation of tangible assets, or that showing new measurements are used to give further insight in the organization. All this is related to the term intellectual capital, which has been defined in many ways. It is about those intangible assets that do not show up on financial statements but can be codified, valued and managed by the company. It might be knowledge of people that is important to a company. Or it can be said to be the combination of patents, processes, skills, about stakeholders of a company. Economists define it simply as Tobin's-q.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;b&gt;The principles of intellectual capital&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The concern with intellectual capital comes from different sources:
- a more accurate valuation of intangible inputs increase market efficiency through more appropriate flows of capital
- new measurements provide managers with a clearer picture
- to guide future strategy like accounting systems do&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Accuracy in valuations&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Brand valuation, goodwill, human assets accounting are all subjects brought forward in the discussion about truly valueing a company. Still there is a difference between book and market value of companies.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Goodwill on the books is also only what was paid for another company above book value, calculated via &quot;fair&quot; value of the underlying assets. Intangible assets can be valued by accountants by finding out their market value. The difference between what the accountant then says the company is worth and what you pay is goodwill.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The difference between accounting data and share prices has increased over the last 30 years as more value is attached to intangible assets that cannot be monetized. Data from 1992 suggests that 40% of the value of a company is missing from the books, something that is subscribed to intellectual capital assets by some.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Tobin's q is a measurement of that really in that it calculates the ratio between market and book value. But the market value is more about investor attitude towards the value of the firm than an objectifiable value. Bubbles on the stock market are still happening even though we know they exist and the collapse of confidence brought forward by investors. Once some speculators cash in, it might create a panic and the bubble bursts. This then turns out to be a self-reinforcing process. Can we remove that bubble with good intellectual capital accounting?&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Internal efficiencies are another thing driving intellectual capital measurement. Companies want to be worth more or know what they are worth at least. Some studies seem to show that an increase in published R&amp;D expenditure increases market value. Another link seems to be between expenditure on advertising and market value. These costs seem to lead to a reaction that would suggest and increase in assets instead of costs.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In that, companies need to manage all their assets including knowledge. The better you measure all your assets, the more easily you detect opportunities and all allocate resources better. This I actually buy into. You can also measure to read a goal, meaning that you look at where you stand and if your base is capable of supporting you in reaching your goal.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;So what drives intellectual capital measurement:
- Market inefficiencies
- Internal inefficiencies
- Measurement to reach goals&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;We can then group intellectual capital into some categories:
- knowledge
- information
- communication
- human resources
- brands
- copyright
- patents
- systems&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Roos and Roos identify a three-stop process:
- nurturing an intellectual capital language
- identifying intellectual capital indicators
- developing an intellectual capital report&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You might not agree to all of this but one thing that is sire is that current performance measurement is sub-optimal to predict future financial performance. Strategic decisions need full information, which is not anything new really. The link of IC to market value should now be clear though.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The language of intellectual capital&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The vocabulary is important to make the areas of focus and concern clear. The process to build the vocabulary should be continuous, being fitted and refitted to your necessary focus and concern. There are some intellectual capital methods that can be noted:
- Kaplan and Norton's Balanced Scorecard
- Skandia's Navigator
- Karl Sveiby's Intangible Asset Monitor
- The IC Index&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;They often are similar in their categories of concern:
- human capital
- infrastructure
- intellectual property
- franchise value / customer capital
- renewal and development
- process
- ...&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In the end the areas of concern need to be indicators of future performance. Financial measurement as sales show past performance. Customer loyalty or satisfaction might show future performance. An intellectual capital language is looking at future performance. There are several areas of concern that might be a good starting point:
- Information sharing because good capacity means good ability to re-use
- Networks, communication &amp; and innovation (e.g. 3M)
- Intellectual property
- Brands
- Talent/Human resources&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;These are again just examples though.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In summary, you need three steps. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broadly define intellectual capital.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify subgrouped areas of concern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify elements that contribute to future success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;It must be pointed out that even though you find a potential element it might not contribute to the company intellectual capital. In a sense you might have to move back from 3 to 2 for further discussion and re-evaluation. The process should never end.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Measureing Intellectual Capital&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the root up: Find your concerns and then ask those at the core how they should be measured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recap: a) Nurture IC language. b) Identify IC indicators. c) Develop IC Report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intro to measures: Many measures will not be monetary but they might be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discounted Cash Flow: Patents and Copyrights are often valued like that, via future cash flows discounted by a discount factors, which can still be wrong though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monetary Measures: e.g. amount spent on training, R&amp;D expenditure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ratio Measures: This gives a relative performance indicator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Absolute Numbers: Number of scientists for example. But there needs to be a sound justification for exactly that number.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subjective: More used to augment a measure. Do you find working here a pleasant experience rated between 1 and 5 can best be used to support another measure but not as the only one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a new method: In the financial market you always compare, yet here you are only looking inside which might mean that it is respected too much outside the organization as a measure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;B&gt;Examples of measurement methods&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Skyrme argued that these systems are currently in a stage of evolution, being refined over time.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The balanced scorecard
It was introduced 1992 in an HBR article by Kaplan and Norton based on a year-long study at 12 companies. There are four perspectives: financial, customer, internal business, innovation and learning. They are often interlinked, influencing each other and need to be based on areas of focus and concern. The main idea is that you put control of vision and strategy while implementation is done by others. It focusses on the drivers or lead indicators of future performance. Some examples are on page 40 of the book or likely to be found all over the net.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Skandia Navigator
Skandia, the swedish financial services company, is one of the leaders in IC measurement. If I remember correctly they are also on the forefront of a move to remove budgets totally. Anyway, they look at: financial, customer, human, process, and 'renewal and development'. the human focus is at the center with the systems there to help managers figure out their appropriate measurements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are only very few measures in their system but they have been refined over a long period. Skandia believes the measurement system shows how Skandia can create financial capital from intellectual capital. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The intangible assets monitor
Karl Eric Sveiby developed it, designating four categories of concern:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internal structure: patents, concepts, models, systems, ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;External structure: relationships, brands, trademarks, reputation, ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;Individual&quot; competence: employee ability to act, skills, education, experience, eq, ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Competence belongs to be individual he believes but the company cannot be conceived without people. Each of these categories is then measured to see whether it aids stability, efficiency, or growth and renewal. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The IC Index
Göran and Roos combine some larger focus areas into an &quot;efficiency&quot; index. Different areas of focus are combined to form an index. Some examples are on page 44.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;B&gt;Additional points&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The report needs to include the following:
- How did IC become important to use
- How does it fit our objectives
- Explanation of areas of concern
- Measures in tables and charts&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The reader of a company report needs to be introduced to the specific measures as they are very specific to the company. The idea is that if the measures are accurate (financial reporting is a science too), the market will reward it and become more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Then you also need to assess the need. It is certain that regulatory bodies like the SEC will require more IC accounting as standard account is only showing the past. Several studies show that the benefits outweigh the costs.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Steward actually believes that utilizing your intellectual capital means exploiting the &quot;free-floating brainpower&quot; of individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Critique of ICM Programs&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is merely repackaging of managing people (Boudreau)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we already have benchmarking, competence models, business worth, ... all the other reports that are similar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can the data really correspond to the question? Sample bias, missing data, the difference between correlation and causation, playing the numbers, ... all play a role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power (1994) raised the question whether any audit system is not flawed and only uses up valuable resources. This is because the data can easily be misinterpreted, because of the increase of likelihood of group think, becoming entrenched in the numbers and whether that what is audited is really important of whether something else is not simply missed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Context of the auditor matters and might be unfit. What, how and if something is audited is influence by the receivers of the audit. There is likely one way. And who audits the auditors?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potential for fraudulent behavior is big (playing the numbers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extra-Organizational Knowledge Processes]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/01/12/extra-organizational-knowledge-processes/"/>
    <updated>2005-01-12T20:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/01/12/extra-organizational-knowledge-processes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;External markets exist and perfect competition doesn't, so sometimes you have more knowledge, something you have to decide to give to or take from the market. Machlup (1962) fond that 29% of GNP of the USA was coming from knowledge production. The public wants knowledge public as markets ensure the best use of all available knowledge.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>Companies might also want external knowledge, to get new ideas or just because it is cheaper or because they just don't have it internally. This might be as of Porter a way to gain new capabilities. Sometimes companies also share knowledge. If knowledge can be patented there is little risk and a lot of upside in terms of licensing. Otherwise secrecy might be the best option but the idea of communities of practice, with researchers publishing papers for status, might bring more to the table than potentially is list.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Edge (1979) argued that especially scientists need informal networks to keep up to date. Specialized knowledge has extra value and is extra expensive to generate. On top of that it is increasingly created in the market. Gibbons talked about Mode 1 and Mode 2 knowledge. Mode 1 is about ideas, methods, is very scientific and the producer and consumer are separated. With Mode 2 however there is a strong application context and group task focus. In reality it is mostly a mix of these two.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The dimensions of knowledge are access to and use of knowledge. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patents, licenses, copyrights allow public access to restricted knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trade associations, conferences and the internet are used best where we are talking about public unrestricted knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If access is private and use restricted, joint ventures, networks and alliances are best used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For private access to unrestricted knowledge, email, phone and face-to-face communication are common.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Institutions and levels&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sectoral level institutions can be guild and trade associations. This is about knowledge shared at the industry level but not beyond. Often these are only an option for a few members of your stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;National level knowledge creation happens in public funds and government sponsored R&amp;D. International collaboration might be needed to share costs, e.g. with particle physics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Governments also need to be able to pick the winners and set policy and directives. In Japan things are a bit different as it is more about continuous improvement and less about Mode 1 knowledge development there. You have a more collective tacit knowledge too. The government in Japan does a lot of work on foresight databases and studies, taking the broader picture approach.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Foresight approaches are newer in Europe and less structured there and in the USA. IT is also seen as expensive and the industry runs more in the trial and error system.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;B&gt;Intellectual property&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Regulatory systems created intellectual property legislation, looking at recognizing an author and setting terms for protection. IP legislation is only following technological advances though, which among others decrease the cost of production and transaction, hence increasing things that might be seen as privacy. Some believe that the power of IP is getting out of hand though.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are two branches here:
IP is about prior registration for a wide range.
Copyright is working without registration, with creative commons being a new model here.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Global systems of administration are the World Intellectual Property Organization (WIPO) with 170 member states and the World Trade Organization (WTO).&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;B&gt;Collaboration networks and alliances&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are different kinds of networks and they relate to the need of trust, sharing power, knowledge and information. As Kanter points out they also increase your relationship knowledge which is mostly tacit. The boundary between internal and external knowledge becomes fluid with networks.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Alter and Hage (1993) provided a categorization of types of collaboration which can be seen in Table 4.1. and 4.2.. They believe that inter-organization collaboration is an ongoing process.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;What is a network organization thought? An organization is already a pattern of roles and relationships, but here we have more integration across formal boundaries (Baker, 1992). The changing linkages and loose boundaries increase flexibility. people are allocated to problems and projects. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;McKiernan (1992) identified 7 basic premises of network theory:
- networks relate organizations
- dependence on each other is high
- resources are firm unique (mostly)
- networks are in a flux
- strengths depend on links (knowledge is valued highest at the point of highest need which might not be with you)
- information exchange is key
- product and service characteristics influence bonding.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;They are promising in fast changing technology markets but do not only have benefits but also costs. You no longer follow a strategy of killing competitors and control. You go for cost, speed and co-operation. Competition is now amongst groups. Alter and Hage argue that there are four factors necessary for a network to work:
- willingness to cooperate
- need for expertise
- need for funds
- need for adaptive efficiency&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Dupond formed a virtual laboratory for example. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You do need a strategic fit (complementarity) and cultural fit (trust, ...). Inter organizational dealings are complex:
- less rules and more experience driven
- conflicts are resolvable
- grant autonomy
- operational rules can't replace contact
- co-ordination through mixed teams&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Miles et al believes that the cellular organization is coming in light of Mode 2 knowledge gaining importance in a complex world. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Technology transfer is the way knowledge is transfered across boundaries. Howells argued that lack of attention to tacit knowledge can lead to downfall. Technology transfer is among others driven by cost, time, desire for new areas to work in and acknowledging the increase in creativity through networks. There needs to be a mutual benefit for it to work.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are two main points in this chapter. For one, it is written in the context of rapid change. Because the way knowledge is produced, especially in Mode 2 knowledge, you need to look outside your own organization.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
