<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OUBS | Oliver Thylmann]]></title>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/categories/oubs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-10T11:31:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://thylmann.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oliver Thylmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Organizing for Innovation]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/10/16/organizing-for-innovation/"/>
    <updated>2004-10-16T19:44:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/10/16/organizing-for-innovation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;This will be a very short item this time, summarizing the third book of this course. I am actually done but I'd like to have some things online searchable so I can find them. There we go. This one is about innovation in general and how to set up a corporation for it.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>First of you need to think about the fact that there is both radical and incremental improvement and if you remember the innovation pyramid, 85% of all innovation is incremental. There is very little radical innovation. Sources where innovation come from are dissatisfaction with the status quo, or at the managerial level a remedy for failure or at a strategic level a simple response to external events. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Two models existed early on. The technology push model (basic science -&gt; design and engineering -&gt; manufacturing -&gt; marketing -&gt; sales) neglected the role of the market and the expensive side of basic research. The market pull model (market need -&gt; development -&gt; manufacturing -&gt; sales) is used for 80% of products but you will not be at the forefront and develop the new thing that will find a market.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Neither of the two did really seem to be the right thing which lead to the coupling model in the 1970s which coupled all steps with an ear to the market and underlying state of the art technical systems and development. This still looked at things sequentially though just incorporating connections and feedback. In the 1980s this led to the integrated model which is more parallel and overlapping. Today we are even moving to something Rothwell calls 5G, the system integration and networking model, which is modeled around integration, flexibility, networking and real time information processing as well as the ability to learn.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Then we have an innovation life cycle:&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Innovation -&gt; Product life cycle -&gt; key features improved -&gt; dominant design -&gt; innovation diffused to a wider audience -&gt; new innovation challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Abernathy and Utterback found that first a wave of new firms come into a market and then something called the dominant design takes hold. This is a new product that is a mix between technological innovations introduced independently in previous products they argue. This is the point when true size is gained but also when the industry becomes more vulnerable again. Things become more standardized, mindsets get fixed and marketing-led management takes over from technology-led management. This is why you get vulnerable to disruptive technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The rate of innovation goes up with product innovation, then process innovation takes over, more competitors get in and then the innovation shrinks. So how to become innovative? Can you copy. Of course! :) It's called creative swiping and Kay argues that copying can be a lot more profitable. Then there is benchmarking which became the legal form of copying in the 1980s, with Xerox first establishing benchmarking for their products and then also for their processes. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;But you still need to go through repeated failure and introspection, argues Soichiro Honda, and cooper and Kleinschmidt identified three key factors for success:
- Product advantage - unique features
- Proficiency of predevelopment activities - initial screening
- Protocol / definition - target market&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The idea screen needs to make clear that a good idea is not enough it needs to fit resources, capabilities, finances, structure and values of a company. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Keeping with value, the most of it is in the intellectual capacity of a company in these times, especially its tacit knowledge. How to get that out of people? One would be suggestion schemes but here you need to pay attention that you:
- publicize the scheme
- give feedback about all suggestions
- act upon a subset of them
- publicize what you have done&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;People like to be recognized and you might not even need financial rewards, 3M for example doesn't. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;So when do you go to market? You can be first to market (Intel) with strong R&amp;D offering a temporary monopoly. You can be a fast follower (AMD) with nimble development and engineering capability. Then you can also be the one late to market (NEC) with product, process or economies of scale offering cost advantages. A niche specialist (Transmeta) will focus on special applications.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;What will happen in the future is also important and scenario building will help you prepare. You will not be able to know what happens in the future anyway, but preparing is important. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Another important field are structures and boundaries. We are moving to more and more a projects based enterprise. Maybe in the future only the core of the company will really be fixed and the rest will be moving around. Projects are mostly interdisciplinary, co-operative and transient, normally a fixed thing in a fixed timescale. There are different structures:
- basic relay structure: projects move from department to department
- matrix organization: teams made up from different departments but this can be an extra stress
- independent project: full time transfer for big projects
- venture team: outside standard reporting structure
- dual structure: routine tasks done by organization and then there is a project network.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that the dual structure will have a huge future. Then you can also look outside of the company. You can do partnerships here or joint ventures, mergers or simply build up networks.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Quality is another important point mentioned, going from quality inspection, over quality control, on to quality assurance and finishes at TQM. It was greatly influenced by Deming who argued that people mattered and that it was management's task to get out of the way. This brings us to the final point of the final point of the empowerment staircase. You move from informing, to communicating to consultation to co-determination to control. You just need to find the stage that fits your corporation.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;So there you go, I told you it was short. :) Next course, Knowledge Management. Kick ass. Already setting up a Wiki at this time :)&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Problems Creatively: Precepts]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/08/30/managing-problems-creatively-precepts/"/>
    <updated>2004-08-30T20:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/08/30/managing-problems-creatively-precepts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;(comment: As originally posted on the <a href="http://blog.thylmann.net/category/oubs/">OUBS Blog</a>)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of different techniques you can use, and some ordering is needed. For the OUBS this is done with 12 precepts as a framework. These can be grouped together further in terms of their giving a sense of direction, or being part of Handy's creative climate (Curiosity, Forgiveness, Love). Underpinning all of this is Schon's idea of the &quot;reflective practitioner&quot;, meaning somebody that goes into deep double-loop learning.
I'll now give a very short overview over these. While they are easy to grasp as a first step. Most of them have some deeper meaning that needs some thinking on your part. I highly suggest taking each part and think about what this really means for you, potentially going back to the book to get some insight.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Curiosity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Precept 1: Adopt a 'set to break sets'&lt;/em&gt;: Think different, get people that think different, take different perspective, different different different&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Precept 2: Explore the 'givens'&lt;/em&gt;: Context is important for a problem. Maybe the context was wrong. Use Assumption surfacing or Reversals to get behind it. Get a fresh view on it. Try being very clear about your environment, trying to notice things you take for granted.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Precept 3: Broad picture, local detail&lt;/em&gt;: You can store an enormous amount of information, but only very few items at a time. Use mind maps or similar techniques to go broad and deep at the same time or rather one after the other.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forgiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Precept 4: Value play&lt;/em&gt;: Play is central to learning, just think about being a kid. You learn by trial and error. It loosens things up if you can just play with a problem. For this you need to create a special settings, choose team members that trust each other and you can simply use such techniques as a way to build a team.
&lt;em&gt;Precept 5: Build up, don't knock down&lt;/em&gt;: Go from 'Yes, but...' to 'Yes, and...'. Value people.
&lt;em&gt;Precept 6: Live with Looseness&lt;/em&gt;: Things will be confusing, uncertain, contradictory, sceptical and more. Especially in whicked problems you need to live with it and let go to have a map built over time.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Love&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Precept 7: It is there already - nurture it&lt;/em&gt;: Creativity is probably already there, well below its potential. Try removing soem barriers. Delegate, make ideas welcome, schedule idea time.
&lt;em&gt;Precept 8: Involve others&lt;/em&gt;: We all have different view, and something normal for us might not be for somebody else. New ideas come from this. Enjoy the differences.
&lt;em&gt;Precept 9: Connect and be receptive&lt;/em&gt;: ideas can be triggered from your environment. These can be related to the problem or not. You need to link problems and triggers.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A sense of direction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Precept 10: Know what you really want&lt;/em&gt;: As they say &quot;if you don't know where you want to go, you probably won't get there&quot;. The way is not important, or rather needs to be loose, but the goal should be clear.
&lt;em&gt;Precept 11: Cycle often and close late&lt;/em&gt;: Try not to appear decisive, or stop at the first solution. Cycle a few times to allow extra deeper information to filter in.
&lt;em&gt;Precept 12: Manage the process&lt;/em&gt;: People, Place and Process. These are important and should be managed.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Being a reflective practitioner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep creativity and analysis apart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep records&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand what you are doing and why&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn from the experience of others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There is a nice checklist on page 113 of the book for self-evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to kill creativity by Teresa Amabile]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/05/20/how-to-kill-creativity-by-teresa-amabile/"/>
    <updated>2004-05-20T14:15:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/05/20/how-to-kill-creativity-by-teresa-amabile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;Amabile argues that creativity is a function of three components: expertise, creative thinking skills, and motivation.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>Managing creativity was what Amabile researched and she has found six general categories that are important for the manager.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Challenge
You need to match people with the right assignements, with the perfect stretch. This means you need to know the people and the assignements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom
You need to give people the autonomy concerning the means/process but not necessarily the end. In some way I might even argue that some people need to know the end and don't want to find it themselves. If you set the goals, you need to make sure that they stay stable or meaningful for a longer period in time, as switching goals kill freedom. Autonomy needs to be really granted, not only in name.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Resources
You have time and money to consider here. Time pressure can heighten creativity or kill it. Increasing intrinsic motivation through a challenge is good. Fake deadlines help noone and create distrust. What are the funds a team needs to complete their assignement. Adding more resources above what is sufficient will not boost creativity (Comment: depends on definition of sufficient). But keeping resources too tight means people's creativity goes into finding resources. Creative teams need open and comfortable offices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work-group features
You must create mutually supportive groups with diversity of perspectives and backgrounds. Everyone must share the excitement over the team's goals and be willing to help each other and recognize the unique knowledge and perspective that everyone brings. You as a manager need to understand their problem-solving styles and their motivational hot buttons. While homogeneous teams reach solutions more quickly they also agree too fast, killing creativity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supervisory encouragement
To sustain passion people need to feel that their work matters. I would like to extend this to the fact that it needs to matter for something they care about. You need to recognize creative work without offering specific rewards. Remember that ideas must be new and useful but dead ends can end up being enlightening. you might try to serve as a role model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Organizational support
Creativity flourishes when the entire organization supports it. support does not mean bribing people though. Information sharing and collaboration is important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creativity and Perception in Management: Creative Management]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/05/20/creativity-and-perception-in-management-creative-management/"/>
    <updated>2004-05-20T14:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/05/20/creativity-and-perception-in-management-creative-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;We now assume that to add value in our developed economies, we need creativity and innovation. We are shifting from an industrial to the information age with higher pace of change, more uncertainty and a need for more responsive and flexible management. As we need cost reductions, speed increases, flexibility, ... downsizing, delayering, divesting is common. We need to become more efficient. We need to partner and form alliances. And management in all of this is more about perception and facilitation than analysis and control. Creative managmeent is about changing the way organizations are run, opening up their climate and management style, increasing participation and freedom. Enable the organization to innovate and network. Creative management is linked here to transforming organizations while managing innovation is about new product development.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;b&gt;Creative Leaders&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A creative leader has a vision, is charismatic enough to inspire others to follow that vision. A creative manager's role is to attend social needs, ensure open atmosphere and see that ideas can be brought to fruition. Kanter (1991) argued that creative leaders formulate the idea and have the power to advance it. They are good communicators and build coalitions, work through teams and are persistent. They can communicate their vision, inspire and carry their dreams into reality. They have very good social skills. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This is linked to Goleman's (1998) idea of emotional intelligence: self-awareness, self-regulation and  motivation to manage yourself and empathy and social skill to management relationships. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are different leaders though, who could be the Visionary, Entrepreneurial or Transformational leader. Ricardo Semler (1994) goes even further with the self-organizing company. Further information on the different leadership styles can be seen on page 26 of the book. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Creative Managers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Creative endavor is only likely with committed staff. Empowerment and network is key and Morgan (1991) highlights the following properties for today's managers:
- Reading the environment
- Proactivity
- Visionary Leadership
- Human Resource Management
- Remote Management Skills
- Using IT to transform
- Managing complexity
- Contextual Competencies&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;We are moving into an environment where the manager has far less control and has more of a facilitative role. In general, I agree here to the extent that a good manager will make your job easier and this is not about control but it is very hard to let go as a manager. You protect teams from unnecessary obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You need to have the ability to look at situations from different perspectives, taking an overview. Senge (1991) wrote about the importance of mental models and Kanter (1991) used the analogy of a kaleidoscope. Understand the logic and concerns behind different stakeholders' position is very important.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;To be facilitating you need to also allow for sufficient autonomy while still giving stretch and challenge. Kanter (1997) believed you need to offer learning opportunities. Proactivity is about being prepared, potentially using scenarios to play different situations out beforehand. Networking is key because ideas emerge in social settings and employee loyalty is often more to an industry than the firm. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Creative Teams&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Successful teams include people from different styles and backgrounds. There will be a mix of characters. Innovators often competors in their teams for example. Belbin (1988) included the following roles in a team: leaders (task oriented shaper and people oriented chair person), ideas person (creator or plant), resource investigator, monitor-evaluator, team worker, implementer and completer. He later added the specialist.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You often need multi-disciplinary teams with a project leader and (comment: a great sounding job!) the technological gatekeeper who keeps his technical knowledge upt to date through informal networking, as well as a product champion or business sponsor who steers the product through the orgnanization.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The climate needs to be one of freedom, trust, commitment and diversity. Freedom and control of your own work along with good project management and some system of encouragement and feedback are good. Trust is only likely possible in groups of 50 people or less. Pearson (1989) argued for a clear strategy and Kanter (1997) for common values. Stacy (1996) emphasised the capacity to accept ambiguity and uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Organizational Change&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Lots of things are tried here, including continuous improvement, benchmarking, quality, learning, development, knowledge-sharing initiatives, ... . Re-engineering is another idea while Semler's book Maverick, about his own company Semco offeres another radical idea. Remember that most organizational change fails.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In the end, the manager needs to care for employee development, foster collaboration and commitment.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Internal and external finance]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/04/19/internal-and-external-finance/"/>
    <updated>2004-04-19T13:41:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/04/19/internal-and-external-finance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;Finance can be seen similar to a chain of command, just that it is a circle with the front line worker in the end providing the funding through pensions or life insurance. How corporations are run is very important in this entire system and with agency theory alreaddy hinting at the problems to link shareholder and management interest, corporate governance has increased in importance.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>Market-based systems are one form of corporate governance and it's a set of systems and strucutres, the &quot;rules of the game&quot; for top managers, set by the board of directors and showing what stakeholders can expect in how the corporation will be run.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In the USA, ownership and control is generally seperated but arguments have since started with Jensen and Mockling (1970) that this seperation means CEOs will not always maximise shareholder value. In the 1990s option schemes rose to more aling shareholders and managemnt. Now shareholders rebelled as underwater options weren't converted.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Who ownes the companies? In the USA 60% of all shares are held by institutions (pension, mutual, insurance funds, ...). In the UK that's 66%. They control hundreds of billions of dollars worldwide. Their control is limited by a legal need to diversify (UK) and by the Glass Steagall Act (US). With 60 or more firms in their portfolio, they do not have the time, and do not see the need, to closely watch senior management, rather keeping their independetness.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Many investing institutions even give proxy votes to management making it unlikely that any (even organised) vote against management comes through.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Systems for corporate governance could be:
- alignment of management remmuneration to shareholder interest
- board seats to independent non-executive directors representing shareholders
- the market for corporate control, as it is known, simply meaning that shareholders can sell their shares, forcing the stock price down, allowing for a hostile take over
- creditors have high influence
- change of financial statute for realignement&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Increasing gearing meant that the bankrupty risk increased and management has to manage the cash flow more efficiently. This is a new form of LBO (leveraged buyout) if you want.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;MBOs are often used when parts of the company are underperforming due to competition on funds and subsidisation of other parts of the company. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Relationship based systems are more used in Germany, Japan and France. Here the shareholding is less diffuse with large chunks being owned by corporates or banks. Relationships with these large shareholders are long-term and may or may not be formal like via supervisary boards over the board of directors.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Monitoring is the main form here and linking executive pay to the shre price is rare, as are hostile takeovers or mergers. There are even restrictions on voting rights underlying shares limiting them to not allow for control, no matter what the number of shares. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Partly due to the funding needs market-based systems are increasing and shareholder value is starting to replace stakeholder value even though this change is slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Internal v. external reporting&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Internal (management accounting): planning, decision-making, control, often performance is measured.
External (financial accounting): decision making, stewardship, accountability, each stakeholder needs different numbers but the main one in the Anglo-Saxon model is the shareholder anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Financial reports did not aling managers with adding value for shareholders and this has led to linking pay to shareprice via options or shareperformance in relation to an index or other sahre measures. This has lead to senior managers being valued based on economic value-based measured while other managers are  measured on accounting-based measures.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Dillon and Owers (1997) argued that measurement metrics within a management control system need to be:
- consistent with corporate objectives
- perceived to be fair
- variables must be SMART
- inform management when to take action&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Divisional busdget targets are normally set artificially low by the respective managers, to easily meet their targets and this is not inline with senior management objectives to increase revenue per share or economic value.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Leveraged buy-outs targetted firms with apparent low earnings (high P/E) but high cash flows (low P/CF). EV/EBITDA is another value that is often used. DCF brought in the importance of Cost-of-Capital for a firm's value, which LBOs knew. They reduced WACC to improve operations, kind of.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;All this, including dramatic changes in share value not reflected in P/E values drove a rethinking towards cash flow and the importance of WACC. Efficient use of capital resources grew more important than growth for growth's sake.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Economic and accounting measures&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;An external market for corporate control can be most efficient but there is still an attempt to have internal systems. They are related to shareholder value and they look at returns only after those expected by investors. They are based on the concept of economic income, which is the generated income net of investors' ROCI. Economic income started as a concept in the 1930s (Peinreich, 1938):&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Accounting profit = NOPAT = C&lt;em&gt;t (A&lt;/em&gt;t - A_t-1)
where C= cash paid out to owners (all providers of capital)
A = accounting book value&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Economic income = residual income = E&lt;em&gt;t = NOPAT&lt;/em&gt;t - WACC x A_t-1&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This means you show the return after having given all owners the return they wanted for taking the risk of investment in the beginning of the period. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;After that, the value of the company is: V&lt;em&gt;t = SUM ( C&lt;/em&gt;t+n / (1+WACC)<sup>n</sup> )&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;V&lt;em&gt;t = A&lt;/em&gt;t + SUM (E_t+n /(1+WACC)<sup>n</sup> )&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;While the first one is cash flow based, the second one is based on economic value added, but they should give the same values. This is actually similar to NPV in that it looks at the excess return.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;It does require comprehensive income and clean surplus accounting principles though, which are not required at this time. This means that there might need to be 164 changes to the asset values in your books. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In response UK accounting regulators have introduced the Statement of Total Reconised Gains and Losses (STRGL, struggle) working in a clean surplus profit for shareholders method.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The ISB is also encouraging a move to economic vlaue and might require balance sheet items to be quoted in value in use, which requires a DCF method.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Economic income is actually the same as economic value added (EVA), a term trademarked by Stern Steward. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;EVA&lt;em&gt;t = NOPAT&lt;/em&gt;t - WACC x A&lt;em&gt;t-1 = (ROCE&lt;/em&gt;t - WACC) x A_t-1
(As ROCE = NOPAT/A)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;They do argue that due to the already quoted V&lt;em&gt;t calculation, a positive EVA will lead to a higher V&lt;/em&gt;t. And the last formula tell a company to work on activities that earn a ROCE above WACC and to minimise the WACC. The nice thing is that this is relatively easy to understand and this measure can be used both for internal managers as well as shareholders or top management.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Economic income in internal reporting&lt;/i&gt; are gaining popularity (EVA, SVA), but more so in the US than in the UK. They do mostly still use budgets, target profit, target cash flow, value drivers or balanced scorecard. Only 10% use EVA and 15% SVA. In the US, NPV, ROIC, CFROI (real IRR of the investment) or EVA are important. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The problem with NPV is that it is purely a cash flow measure and this is not so readily available in standard management accounting systems. But it is still used a lot for projects.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;ROIC is calculated via NOPAT (adjusted as if there was no debt) and the opening or average capital by long term investors.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;CFROA is both about the future as well as the present and past, but again a cash flow measure and it is inflation adjusted for easier comparison. It has to be compared to cost of capital in real terms and can be used as a means of valueing companies. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;EVA is a money amount and no ratio. It also looks at NOPAT and removes a charge for WACCxAssets. The last three are really saying the same thing in the end. The disadvantage for EVA is that it is not easy to compare companies as it is an accounting measure and Stern Steward said that there are up to 164 accounting adjustments needed to be made to book values to reflect current value of invested capital.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are three main adjustments:
- goodwill that has been written off needed to be added back to invested capital and if deducted from profits added back to NOPAT. Companies that are bought need to earn about WACC on their true book value.
- R&amp;D expenditure needs to be treated as an asset and hence needs to be added back to NOPAT and included in invested capital.
- Leases are part of invested capital as they are seen as debt finance. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Another disadvantage is that EVA is difficult to implement at the divisional level especially as it is very hard to apportion the invested capital of the company. But this is true for every divisional performance measure. Transfer pricing doesn't make things easier. The problem is though that profits do not necessarily add value in terms of EVA.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The last problem is actually applied to value-based metrics in general, is that there is a lot of things like intellectual property, knowledge, IT systems, that aren't fully reflected in the books. It only shows up as goodwill when an acquisition has happened. How do you value employees would be another question.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;On top of that, how do you value social interests in corporate performance? Nobody has found any measures in this space though. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There is also ongoing concern about which measures to use in the public sector. Historically government spending has been monitored on a cash accounting basis. The problem there is that there is no difference made between one-off spendings and spendings on assets that generate future revenue. There is also no incentive to dispose of loss making assets. Government now turned to accruals accounting. This accounting method is introduced in the UK as resource accounting including: operating statement, balance sheet, cash-flow statement, a main objective analysis, output and performance analysis. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;All in all, things are changing from monitoring of inputs to those of outputs, and linking executive pay to it. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Public-Sector Financial Management&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Here things are driving by the VFM, the value for money. This can be linked to the three E's (Economy, Efficiency, Effectiveness) and goes back to the fifth century BC (Dewar, 1989) and has grown in importance in the last two decades. In a move to control spending and improve resource allocation and accountability, there is now a drive towards more private like accounting methods. Now there is some confusion in relation VFM, mostly as there are different objectives, methodologies and standards. It moved from confronting managers about problems, to more checking of management's account of achieving VFM targets. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are several approaches and some can be suggested here (based on Bowerman, 1996):
- Review of management systems, arrangements and procedures (how can value for money be improved)
- Value for money procedures audit (are there objectives and are they checked)
- Policy audit (Are the three E's matched)
- Audit of management represenations of value for money (Is presented information correct)
- comparative performance audit
- Quality audit (e.g. customer satisfaction surveys)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Best value is a new approach, mixing audit and what should be done, including quality. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Performance Measurement and Investment&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;How are investors subject to performance measures is the question of this part. Institutional investors are very important, especially where funds are used for savings in relation to people's pensions. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In measurement of trustee performance it is important that the trustee represents those that gave their trust, and in terms of for example pension funds, this means that they need to be able to pay out the promised pensions, known as the minimum funding requirement. Above and beyond that, they should maximise the returns over the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;These trustees do not need to know anything about investments, as they delegate that part of internal or external fund management. External fund management companies are growing strong and their managers make presenations to the trustees. They do need to maximise return but reduce risk through diversification. They need to report quarterly which might even make them perform less optimally in relation to their goal. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;These funds also use the matching principle, meaning that they will try to match their investments with their required payouts. The fund managers that run these funds will try to stick close to the median of all pension fund managers as they are normally measured in relation to other fund managers and only need to be top of the list. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The problem is that these investments sometimes don't follow CAPM, which would predict that with no prior expectation, investments should mirror market size internationally. But should trustees follow the herd and invest where CAPM predicts of where the average UK fund manager invests. If they take the CAPM approach, they might end up in the bottom band of UK fund management companies. This would be a breach of their contract to optimize performance. But without it they didn't take advantage of USA stock rises as best they could, which they would have with CAPM.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Also, some pension funds add an ethical bit to the mix, excluding for example tabacco companies. This also can cause underperformance.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;So how should the fund managers be measured. They will have to outperform and this can be done through better asset allocation than the median or a better stock selection than the benchmark. In the past they didn't do well in asset allocation in general, not predicting US stock rise and being over-optimistic on Japan. Managers do believe that markets are not efficient at one level because they do believe that they can consistently outperform via their stock picks. With a higher return, they normally also have a higher tracking error (standard deviation on top of comparison index)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Many trustees are switching to passive funds.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
