<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Strategy | Oliver Thylmann]]></title>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/categories/strategy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-10T11:31:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://thylmann.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oliver Thylmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book 10: International Strategies: Competing Across Borders]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/10/09/book-10-international-strategies-competing-across-borders/"/>
    <updated>2003-10-09T19:54:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/10/09/book-10-international-strategies-competing-across-borders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Originally published on <a href="http://blog.thylmann.net/category/oubs/">OUBS Blog</a>)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em /&gt;Even if you do not carry out international activities within your organisation, you will be affected by international trade and strategies of MNCs (Multinational corporations). Delivering robust strategies across borders is very dynamic and complex.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internation competition: the management of internation trade&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Activities of multinationals are based on foreign direct investment (FDI), which also led to much of internation trade now being internal to these MNC, who oversee immense resources rivaling all but the richest countries. Over time, the overseas parts of the companies became more independant with managers tasks being planning, control and administration. Now the entire value chain could be redesigned. High skills in co-ordination and integration across borders are needed. This skill has lead to the emergence of partnerships and alliances.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The law of comparative costs and comparative advantage underlies all international trade and countries have different capabilities in land, labour and capital.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Porter (1990) identified some factors of production influencing international movements:
- internationally mobile factors of production (mobility of labout increasing)
- fast-changing technology
- mobility barriers, entry or exit barriers&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;To gain competitive advantage, the following factors play a role:
- human resources
- physical resources
- knowledge resources
- capital resources
- infrastructure&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand where a competitive advantage comes from though. In the case study about Komatsu and Caterpillar, Komatsu's formulation and implementaion of a long-term strategy to become established in world markets, enabled existing sources of comparative advantage (cost) to support internation competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are four main types of international trade:
- exporting
- Foreign direct investment
- licensing
- joint ventures or strategic alliances&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Rugman et al. (1985) developed a rational decision tree to decide which one is right for you.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Are there barriers to free trade?
-&gt; No -&gt; Export
-&gt; Yes
Is there a risk of dissipation of knowledge
-&gt; Yes -&gt; FDI
-&gt; No -&gt; License
-&gt; Containable
But is there a resource limitation?
-&gt; Yes -&gt; Strategic alliance&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Remember that the approach needs to fit your company, industry and time... and of course your company :)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You can either be:
- Multinational: decentralised and self-sufficient in each nation, working with local opportunities, retaining knowledge within units
- Global: centralised but scaled globally, implementing the strategies of the parent company, with knowledge at the center retained
- International: core competencies central, using parent company capabilities, knowledge from center outwards
- Transnational: dispersed, interdependent, specialised, different contributions integrated, knowledge jointly developed and shared&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Governments play a large role though, in both directions, as they also have to cope with MNCs moving elsewhere. The regulatory authority is there 'to provide the conditions for the market to work and if necessary correct potential excesses.'&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The benefit of being an MNC is that you have more flexibility and options. You can try to exploit those barriers that are good for you and avoid the others. Large organisations have some advantages here, identified by Kogut (1985) as:
- production shifting
- tax minimisation
- financial markets
- information arbitrage
- global co-ordination
- reducting political risk&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparative Advantage and International Competitive Advantage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Kogut suggested that &quot;&lt;em&gt;Gobal strategies rest on the interplay of the competitive advantage of firms and the comparative advantage of countries.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;National markets are now becoming only parts of a global market and levers for internationalisation can be said to be world trade and FDI. Porter's national 'diamond' is interesting here to understand the different in national positions. Here Demand Conditions; Factor Conditions; Firm Strategy, Structure and Rivalry; Related and Supporting Industries interact.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Next, looking at the value chain. Configuration refers to where the value chain activities are performed and a choice of configuration can be a source of advantage. Co-ordination is about how it is managed. These two interact, as the co-ordination needs to be between different parts dependent on how the value chain is configured. There are three different options for the value chain, one being scale efficiencies by putting on part of the value chain in one location and putting them emphasis here. The other option would be seek efficiency in each link of the chain and the last option would be to look across the entire chain and optimize the linkages across it.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Ghoshal's organisation framework is helpful in finding out what the point is of a global strategy. In the frame work there are
Strategic objectives:
- Achieving efficiency in current operations
- Managing risks
- Innovation, learning and adaptation&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;and Sources of competitive advantage
- National differences
- Scale economics
- Scope economics&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The point of a global strategy would then be on of the strategic objectives, achievable through the said competitive advantages&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Economy of scope can be best defined through the example of Gillette buying Duracell.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;using a resource [a global distribution network for razors] acquired for one purpose for additional purposes [selling batteries] at little or no extra cost.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Industries and International Firms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are different strategies here:
- Multidomestic or Multilocal = each country or region on a stand-alone basis
- Global = integrated approach&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There can also be a mix in global strategy for some products and regional one for others, depending on what is warranted for the product. As markets are converging and differences (social, economic and cultural) shrinking, there are more options to at least go global on part of your strategy, building arround a standardised core while offereing local variations.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Some argue though that the problem starts to appear that there are real differences between countries and even intra-country fragmentation happening. Maybe the standardisation has gone too far.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Ikea has benefited from building universal appeal for their products, allowing standardised marketing and distribution. You can benefit in global operations from: design, purchasing, manufacturing operations, packaging, distribution, marketing, advertising, customer service and software development. Mixing advantages from global operations and local ones is known as glocalisation. A good example here is that the chinese would like their shampoos in sachets rather than bottles and buy them in barber shops. This is something that needs to be known but the same shampoo as such, the same production process, etc. can still potentially be used.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are different kinds of international firms. The most advanced system of those is what Bartlett and Ghoshal (1993) named 'beyond the M-form', with M for multidivisional. Rather it's an emerging N-form with N standing for network. Here the importance is on co-ordination and providing a shared corporate purpose.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In service industries you are selling an intangible experience. Globalisation is about delivering a similar service for a mobile customer base. The service needs to be consistent and often the customer internationalises first. Branding is an important part of providing, or at least suggesting a quality and consistency across borders. Staff training is very important here and the more can be decoupled from the customer into the back-office value chain, the grater the reconfiguration advantages for scale and scope.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Strategy Development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The decision tree should tell you that in absense of barriers of free trade, you should simply export. If there are no risk of dissipating knowledge, then FDI is needed. The mid way would be a strategic alliance.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You need to take into account the partners' cultures, attitude and expectations as well as the potential loss of control and limit of alternative opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Reason for strategic alliances might be:
- faster penetration and exploitation of key markets
- new strategic directions otherwise not possible
- potential payoffs higher than costs
- immediate access
- cost-reduction
- synergies
- need for complex resource bundles
- safety by spreading financial risks, novelty risks, political risks, volatility, standards
- a way of building defences&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Harrigan argued that &lt;em&gt;alliances fail because operating managers do not make them work, not because contracts are poorly written.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Faulkner (1994) found four factors for successful management of alliances:
- positive partner attitudes
- clear organisational arrangements
- a learning philosophy
- congruent long-term goals&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are several types of analysis:
- joint ventures
- collaborations
- consortia&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;To make them work you can use a gateway system, a gatekeeper to avoid misunderstandings. The mission of gateway executives is boundary-spanning. You should also only gradually increase areas of involvement for incompatibilities to be reduced. Many successful alliances also have divorce procedures.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book 9: Corporate Strategy]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/08/31/book-9-corporate-strategy/"/>
    <updated>2003-08-31T21:23:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/08/31/book-9-corporate-strategy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Originally published on <a href="http://blog.thylmann.net/category/oubs/">OUBS Blog</a>)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Corporate strategy signifies an overarching strategy, above and beyond that of one of the businesses of that corporation. The idea is to achieve superior returns through the combination of different businesses.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The book starts with a case on VWs acquisitions of Seat and Skoda and the potential benefits achieved through the integration and combination of those. For one, the company now has different brands in different market segments, but built on a standard platform to achieve economies of scale and scope. The problem that starts to appear is that the differentiation between the different brands is shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;VW is saving some $500 million but this is only an advantage as long as Ford or Toyota cannot cut the costs the same amount.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;All this combination stuff has come from portfolio management, which is about combining a portfolio of diversified strategic business units. Important here is also BCG's growth-share matrix. The idea is to use internal cash flows for financing and manageing the cycle of declining businesses and growing ones. You take the stars, invest in them to make them cash cows which will provide the cash for the next stars.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The problem with portfolio management is that the only idea behind it is the management of cash flows. In the late 1980s, strategy moved back to focussing on core businesses. The thing is that in balancing cash cows and stars, the manager acts as the shareholder. The shareholder can do that himself though and it is sometimes unclear where the manager can add value or if the shareholder should not decide about his exposure to risk himself. Agency theory even suggests that portfolio diversification is bad for shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Now in the 1990s, strategy moved away from markets and more to capabilities though, which brings us to the notion of synergies.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The thing is that merely putting some companies in a portfolio does not add value, but synergy will need to be created, managed. The idea is to combine activities so that 2+2 = 5 (which can also fail and end up as 3 :)). The thing is that you need to clearly identify what the capabilities will be that will be needed for the synergies to work out.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Complementary benefits can be achieved through combination of physical assets for economies of scale, higher capacity utilisation and an improved product mix. Invisible assets may also be transfered from one business to another.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Itami (1992) suggested that there are combinatorial benefits, like opening a resort for the summer in a sky resort, and synergy which is multiplicative rather than additive, e.g. that by good reputation visitors in any season might come in the other too.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The thing is that some things are limited by some thing like for example capacity. Using a Plant that is used 70% more, can only lead to 100% usage, after that it is finished. This is also unlikely to be of lasting effect as other companies can do the same thing in the end. Invisible, information-based assets will likely remain unique to the company and will not run out or be exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Adding time to the mix brings you to static combination benefits, which are the integration of two strategies at one point in time and dynamic combination benefits, where they are integrated over time (e.g. reuse of extraction ptis as waste management depositories). Beyond that we come to dynamic synergy.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Prahalad and Hamel identify companies as collections of core competencies and core products. The thing is that core competencies do not diminish with use, as they put it. Rather, they are enhanced by use. In that sense, markets should be moved in that exploit an existing or develop a new competency. To test if these are core, as yourself:
- do they provide potential access to many markets (is it transferable for combination benefits)
- do they make a significant contribution to the perceived customer benefit of the end product
- are they difficult to imitate&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;If all three fit, the source is likely to be dynamic. Theodore Levitt (1960) argued that many companies focus on their products instead on what the customer wants and one might even argue that they should relate their core competencies to that.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Honda for example did not exploit their products like VW but their core competencies by using the Honda brand across many different products that would not eat away each others profit margins.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Rumelt (1994) established four key components of core competence competition:
- corporate span
- temporal dominance (of products)
- learning-by-doing (to enhance them)
- competitive locus
The thing is that superior corporate performance based on core competencies allows for dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diversification and Divestment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are two possibilities for superior performance, entering an attractive industry or possessing a competitive advantage. What are the motives for diversification in that light?
- growth
- investment risk-spreading
- profitability (evaluated against Porter's (1987) three tests for diversification value-creation)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Economies of scope are the main source of corporate superior performance as of Grant. These need to be more cheaply attained through internalising than out-sourcing (cost economics theory). There is a great figure (3.1) on page 9-26 to test for diversification strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;What if an activity does not work well, should it be divested or a recovery started? Kathy Harrigan (1988) sees declining industies as opportunities for end game strategies. In this game, you can either go for a quick sale, harvest it for cash, find a niche or go for leadership in which you believe that after the others leave, profitabilty will return.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Harrigan believes that companies either need to flee or fight. Grinyer et al. (1988) studied strategies with companies in delicne followed by dramatic and sustained improvement and found something they found sharpbenders. These will often have major management change, improved marketing, reduced production costs, improved quality and service.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Another usefulness of core competencies is that they allow you to see if you should divest and risk loosing that competency. Otherwise it might be wise to outsource.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategies for corporate structure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In Book 7 Alfred Chandler's (1962) thesis was that 'structure follow strategy'. Rumelt (1974) argued that for some 'structure follows fashion'. Divisionalised structure was very in fashion until the 1970s, when the advantage of adopting it was removed as everybody was doing that. Corporate strategy as a management activity originated from the structure though.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The thing is that co-ordination and decentralisation are not easy to reconcile. Especially when leveraging invisible assets or core competencies, or at least trying too. You should also not forget the national interest and government policy when thinking about corporate strategy and the potential structure it entails or brings with it.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Chandler's work (1962) was born out of the thesis that the devisionalised corporation evolved out of diversification and growth strategies of large enterprises. The thing is though that in different social and economic conditions things work very differently, which is examplified in a case about russias emerging conglomerate corporations. Here the setting that things were taking place in, needed some specific strategies which resulted in some specific structures.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This leads us to the idea that corporations need  to understand values and norms behind competitors' strategies. In the UK and USA there is a market oriented relationship between shareholders and corporations. In the Rhenish model banks play a more important role for long-term loan and equity, bringing more friendly capital and stability. In Japan, companies often have their origins in diversified, family-controlled zaibatsu merchant houses of the seventeenth century. Here the subsidiaries raise 49% of the cash needed for the company letting the family maintain control. These zaibatsu have evolved into keiretsu, involving interconnected members with support from keiretsu banks with interlocking minority shareholding.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You therefor need to understand regulation, government, socio-economics and cultural context to really see the structures in their full bloom.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Multidivisional structure removed the responsibility for the entire enterprise from routine operational tasks. Responsibility was often pushed down with minimal interconnections between different parts of the same corporation, with profit centers being decentralized resulting in less gains from scale and scope and less coherence of the corporation as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The thing is that if superior performance is about synergy and compination, then decentralisation might be a bad move. Management can managed the corporate portfolio, invididual business or internal linkages. This is not an easy dilemma and managers will always have to choose between centralisation or decentralisation and integration or independence and control or collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Networks and Corporations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;One thing you can do is to accept this tension and get away from it (Sloan, 1963). In Japan instead of a formal hierarchy there are informal networks based on trust and relationships. A simple choice of make or buy is not enough here, even though the structures can be critized for less than free flow of information and capital in the general market.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Kay (1993) identified co-operative relational contracting as an alternative to classical or spot contracts. In Europe these might be:
- network of italian suppliers for benetton
- professional service firms who link complementary skills or locations&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Four main drivers might encourage the formation of networks:
- rising global competition
- deepening industry convergence
- battels over technical standards
- positioning&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In the end, we need to extend 'make or buy' to 'make, buy or co-operate'. The corporate management needs to include network co-ordination then, co-ordinating joint decision-making. For alliances to fulfil their obligations Gomes-Cassares identified two main methods:
- establishing group norms and standards
- leadership in group decision-making (network leader or agreed compromise or consensus method)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The tighter the collaboration, the blurrier the boundary, the more the joined the firms are and the more will they put their economic weight into the battle as one unit.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Potential sources of advantage for networks come from:
- flexible capabilities
- specialisation and division of labour
- learning
- increased options&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Remember though that networks are very complex, in itself and to be managed.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book 8: Organisational capabilities: culture and power]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/08/30/book-8-organisational-capabilities-culture-and-power/"/>
    <updated>2003-08-30T15:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/08/30/book-8-organisational-capabilities-culture-and-power</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;em&gt;(Originally published on <a href="http://blog.thylmann.net/category/oubs/">OUBS Blog</a>)&lt;/em&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;em /&gt;The organisational paradigm are the beliefs and assumptions that make up &quot;an organisation's view of itself and its environment&quot; (Johnson, 1988). Together with:
- stories and myths
- symbols
- rituals and routines
- control systems
- organisational structures
- power structures
- symbols
it builds the &quot;cultural web&quot; or an organisation.</p>

<p>Deal and Kennedy (1982) defined culture as 'the way we do things around here'. Some of the elements of the cultural web are formal mechanism and others are informal. The meaning of those are what is significant. This is again made visible through the stories and myths, often used for sensemaking of events and hence not always accurate but more about getting the point across. Stories can be enhanced through rituals and routines.</p>

<p>A richer culture definition comes from Wilson and Rosenfeld (1990, p.229):</p>

<p>&lt;em&gt;...the basic values, ideologies and assumptions which guide and fashion individual and business behaviour. These values are evident in more tangible factors such as stories, ritual, language, and jargon, office decoration and layout and prevailing modes of dress among staff.&lt;/em&gt;</p>

<p>This shows that organisational culture (what the &quot;other&quot; members value) is a very difficult to define beast, with corporate culture (what the dominant members value) being a small part of it. Often the values of the dominant are more important than of other individuals or even of society.</p>

<p>Culture can also be a capability or resource, also because in case it is a strong and homogeneous one, you might need less formal systems and procedures as control. To homogeneous can also mean group think though, which combined with a limited corporate (rather than organisational) view of culture can lead to too narrow horizons. A strong culture will include commitment to a strategic intent over a long time, making subsequent strategic shifts harder. A culture is a &quot;sticky&quot; factor that locks in an organisation.</p>

<p>In the public sector it is often tried to make responsiveness to the citizen part of the culture.</p>

<p>Many of our deep routed values have been shaped when we were young, teaching us what is right and what is wrong. Not all of them have to be codified in law.  The question is whether working ethically will lead to success and Hosmer (1994) argued that equitable acts lead to trust, which leads to commitment. This commitment, when it is co-operative and innovate, can lead to success. To behave ethically you need to go above the law though, to work within norms and values in a worldwide community/society.</p>

<p>There is a close link between national cultures and organisational cultures, which can be seen in the difference between Japanese and Western way of doing things. The Japanese are using something called 'simultaneous loose-tight coupling' meaning that they have tight conformity to core values with looser control systems. These differences are not only rooted in culture though, but include financial, investment and policy for example. An analysis of 116000 IBM employees in the same or similar jobs found that culture, in relation to nationality, has some distinct dimensions that influence it:
- Power Distance: Acceptance of unequal power distribution
- Uncertainty Avoidance: Tolerance of uncertainty
- Individualism: Personal over Group achievement
- Masculinity: Dominance of masculine tendencies</p>

<p>The paradigm is empirically driven, built on experiences rather than a model of how things should be. They are built on beliefs that have repeatedly been validated. How can managers use this? In a top-down system the manager only pays attention to what he or she wants to pay attention to. In a bottom-up system, the management does not interfere with data.</p>

<p>As strategy making is a collective activity, we need to share each others maps and models of the corporation and the environment to find a collective course of action. This shows again that strategy is not linear and rational but more of a social and cultural contruct. The paradigm defines environmental 'reality'. This makes it a powerful tool for coping with complex situations but also something that is a liability under change conditions. When performance of a company does not work out, we can fist find tighter control of our implementation, then we might reconstruct the strategy and only then would we attack and change our paradigm.</p>

<p>A knowledge creating company needs a special kind of culture and power structure. An example in the book is the middle-up-down process of knowledge management suggested by Japanese economics (Nonaka, 1991; Nonaka and Takeuchi, 1995).</p>

<p>Top down management assumes that only top managers are able to create knowledge and it only exists to be processed and/or implemented. It is good for dealing with explicit knowledge. Buttom-up management makes work autonomous allowing knowledge to be created at the bottom. It is good for tacit knowledge but due to the inherent autonomy this knowledge is extremely hard to communicate.</p>

<p>In the top-down model the fate of the company might be aligned with the fate of a few top managers and bottom-up knowledge creation can be very slow as it rests on the patience and talent of the individual.</p>

<p>Japanese companies seem to create knowledge in the middle management through a spiral conversion process involving top and front-line employees. They serve as the strategic knot. Knowledge can be interpreted differently in a different context and middle-management is used to orient knowledge creation towards a purposeful end, making available frameworks to sense making of new knowledge. Top management creates a dream and middle management develops concrete concepts for the front-line.</p>

<p>&lt;strong&gt;Culture, Power and Change&lt;/strong&gt;</p>

<p>The paradigm is the outcome of all elements of the cultural web and cultural change likely needs to attack this paradigm head on, it must be challenged, discredited and devalued. This can be done by:
- use of an outsider who has little commitment to the current paradigm
- exposing the paradigm
- power reconfiguration
- advocating and legitimising dissent
- powerful advocacy</p>

<p>Senge sees leadership as culture-formation through building shared vision.</p>

<p>In terms of recovery and turnaround strategies there are a few things that generally are done (Slatter, 1984):
- change of management
- strong central financial control
- organisational change and decentralisation
- product-market re-orientation
- improving marketing
- growth via acquisitions
- asset reduction
- cost reduction
- investment
- dept rstructuring and other financial strategies</p>

<p>Important here is cash flow.  It is also important to focus on those 20 per cent of the factors involved that have 80% of the impact (Pareto principle).</p>

<p>&lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt;</p>

<p>Mintzberg (1983): &lt;em&gt;Power is the capacity to effect (or affect) organisational outcomes&lt;/em&gt;</p>

<p>A relationship is needed for power to be present. This relationship leads to interdependencies and then one can argue that power is about the degree of dependence on the othe part of the relationship. The power of a unit can be seen in:
- the importance of the resource
- the control over allocation
- the substitutability of the resource</p>

<p>Important relationships are your stakeholders and the most important ones as of a study chaired by Sir Anthony Cleaver are:
- shareholders
- employees
- customers
- suppliers
- community</p>

<p>The power of any of those relationships depends on your paradigm and the setting of your cultural web.</p>

<p>Remember the following about managing strategy and power:
- power is present in all ofrms of the organisation
- understand power structures and how to management them
- restructure dependencies and resource allocation to manage power
- long-term external relationships are gaining importance and shared expectations are needed here
- you need to balance power</p>

<p>Lord Acton (1887): &lt;em&gt;Power tends to corrupt and absolute power corrupts absolutely.&lt;/em&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book 7: Organisational capabilities: structures and systems]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/08/23/book-7-organisational-capabilities-structures-and-systems/"/>
    <updated>2003-08-23T22:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/08/23/book-7-organisational-capabilities-structures-and-systems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Originally published on <a href="http://blog.thylmann.net/category/oubs/">OUBS Blog</a>)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em /&gt;In this book structure refers to the boundaries of the organisation and the ways the activities inside are co-ordinated. Systems are about information types and flows. Burns and Stalker (1961) describe two possibly systems: mechanistic and organismic.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;structural components, contingencies and configurations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This is based on Henry Mintzberg's article &quot;<a href="http://www.ennead.de/ou/archives/000837.php">The structuring of organisations</a>&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Mintzberg's six ideal structural types:&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Simple Structure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Machine bureaucracy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Professional bureaucracy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Divisionalised form&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Adhocracy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Missionary&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Key part&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Strategic apex&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Technostructure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Operating core&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Middle line&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Support staff&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ideology&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Co-ordinating mechanism&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Direct supervision&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Standardisation of work processes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Standardisation of skills&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Standardisation of outputs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mutual adjustment&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Standardisation of norms&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dominant pull to:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Centralise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Standardise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Professionalise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Balkanise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Collaborate&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Evangelise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Decentralisation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None (centralised)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Limited horizontal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Horizontal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Limited vertical&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Selective horizontal and vertical&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Full decentralisation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Planning and control&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Little&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Action planning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Little&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Much performance control&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Limited action planning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Little&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Liason deviced&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Few&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Few&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In administration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Few&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Many throughout&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Few&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Typical examples&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Small owner-manager firms undertaking simple activities&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fast food chains, airlines, telephone banking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hospitals, colleges, law firms&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Large conglomerates&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creative advertising agencies, bespoke software boutiques&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kibbutz, Revolutionary movements&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Mintzberg argues that &quot;&lt;em&gt;organisations can select their situations in accordance with their structural designs just as much as they can select their designs in accordance with their situations.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy and Systems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;When Daft and Macintosh (1984) studied 86 firms, the same six sub-systems apeared most often for the formulation of strategy:
- strategic plans
- long rang plans (5 years +)
- annual operating budgets
- periodic statistical reports
- performance appraisal
- policies and procedures&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Band and Sanlan (1995) identified some more:
- structural devices like audits
- MIS
- budget and profit planning processes
- HR management arrangements
- R&amp;D programmes
- work practices and norms
- explicit organisational values
- use of external instruments (e.g. benchmarks)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Remember that the information requirements are different from a hierarchical company to an adhocracy and telecommunications often made location less important.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;As a control system for middle management, feedback is the most simply, comparing things to a standard and triggering action at variances. Problems are that there is a log between strategy formulation and feedback, feedback is vulnerable to poor specifications, misunderstanding and the feedback mechanism is sometimes designed too simple, e.g. only based on profitability.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Band and Scanlan (1995) suggest &quot;feedforward&quot; control:
- premise control (are our premises correct?)
- implementation control (are things happening as thought?)
- strategic surveillance (monitor threatening events)
- special alert control (scan for low-probability events)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A more comprehensive approach comes from Simons (1995), using both feedback and feedforward integrating corporate culture.
- Belief systems provide core values that are guiding for business strategy
- Boundary systems  show risks to be avoided
- Diagnostic control systems (e.g. budgets) show critical performance variables
- Interactive control systems (stimulate search and learning) show strategic uncertainties and allow for challenging assumptions&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy, Structure and Systems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You should try to put structure and systems together to form a competitive advantage, a long term one. This will be a changing progression of different strategies, structures and systems, put together by Greiner in 1972.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;(Phase, evolution stages - revolution stages, check Table 4.1)
Phase 1. Growth through creativity leads to crisis of leadership
Phase 2. Growth through direction leads to crisis of autonomy
Phase 3. Growth through delegation leads to crisis of control
Phase 4. Growth through co-ordination leads to crisis of red tape
Phase 5. Growth through collaboration leaders to Crisis of ?&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Miller (1986) tried to show the close fit between strategy and structure:
&lt;em&gt;The theme we wish to pursue here is that there are ties that unite strategy and structure; that given a particular strategy there are only a limited number of suitable structures and vice versa.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Structural change brings a process of organisational innovation, which can as of Chandler (1977) either be an adaptive response or a creative innovation going beyond the existing practices. A Competitive advantage also comes from being different though and hence, after the multidivisional structure had become the norm by the 1970s, firms having adopted it stopped to have superior performance by the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Innovation in structures are always emerging. Some reasons are:
- erosion of advantage through immitation of old ones
- impact of new IT
- competitive pressure for flexibility and low prices
- rapid race for competitive innovation
- competitive focus on time as a source of competitive advantage
- growing importance of knowledge based assets&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Galbraith and Lawler (1993) identified some new functional structures in organizations:
- modified function unit with fewer levels and less functions for faster response
- lateral unit with cross function teams
- superfunctions unit grouped arround core processes e.g. product generation at HP includes R&amp;D, manufacturing and purchasing
- front-end/back-end hybrid (front around customer, end around products with lateral integration)
- network organization (seperate companies integrated through a network)
- function specialist (single function within informal network)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A closer look at those follow.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Transaction cost economics (TCE, Book 4) are used to identify whether to make or buy. An entire organization can be viewed as a system of exchange transactions. Information asymmetry (somebody has different info than somebody else) leads to transaction costs related to incomplete or missing information. This can be:
- search costs
- contracting or negotiation costs
- transaction control, regulation and audit costs
- maintenance costs to develp the contract or transaction&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Based on this belief, the hierarchy was established to overcome imperfections in otherwise efficient markets. Changes in information technology has led to more efficient markets enabling:
- modified function unit uses IT to speed up information flow
- the superfunction unit re-aligns structures with key processes (based on customer needs)
- perfect markets can come from better access to information&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;These are just examples where information technology led to different flows of information enabling radical rethinking of structures&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Network technologies also enable new ways of working with transactions now being conducted through markets, hierarchies and teams.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A lateral unit is a cross-functionl team-based organization like a team of specialists interacting through e-mail, groupware and open databases. The front-end/back-end hybrid requires effective integration of two different structurs with different integration needs to bring a good product or service.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Network organizations require a lead partner to integrate the network and function specialists simply rely on their specialist skills which are needed for a number of different informal networks.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Organization Structure and MAnagement Systems by Grant]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/08/23/organization-structure-and-management-systems-by-grant/"/>
    <updated>2003-08-23T21:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/08/23/organization-structure-and-management-systems-by-grant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Originally published on <a href="http://blog.thylmann.net/category/oubs/">OUBS Blog</a>)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ultimately, there may be no long-term sustainable advantage other than tha ability to organize and manage.&lt;/em&gt; - Jay Galbraith and Ed Lawler&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The evolution of the corporation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;At the end of the 19th century there were only big corporations in plantations, all the rest was personal business with lots of interation between different people. The emergence of factories made the contractor system with market relationships among workers, machine owners and merchants, inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The markets - firms difference is central here. In markets you have price mechanisms which direct the organization and in firms you have managerial direction. Which version you choose depends on efficiency. The idea is that when the administrative costs would be less than the transaction costs in a market, then firms a the more wise choice.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Railroads and the telegraph system allowed for multiple locations to be managed from one central office. Next came the devisionalised structure, the result of margers that started to happen in the 1920s. These started to not be devided by function but also by product. Here the strategic part of centralised while the operational was localised at a devision level.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organizational Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In general an organized human activity, as of Mintzberg, needs division of labor into tasks as well as coordinations of these task to the activity. In terms of division of labor, specialization will lead to immense productivity gains, as long as the coordination need as well as detatchment from the product of the individual does not become too big. Things that can be used for coordination are price (e.g. transfer prices between departments), rules and directives, mutual adjustment and routines.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In general, for individuals to work together, they need to see a reason to do so, something that can be called incentives. Different individuals have different goals though, which leads to the so called &lt;em&gt;agency problem&lt;/em&gt;. Here the Principal contracts with the agent to act on in the principal's interest. An example here would be the use of stock options for managers to allign their interest with that of the shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In the chapter, Bruce Henderson, founder of the Boston Consulting Group is quoted as saying: &quot;&lt;em&gt;Every production man's dream is a factory that always runs at full capacity making a single product that requires no change... every salesman would like to give every customer whatever he wants immediately.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Alignement can be achieved by:
- control mechanisms
- reward incentrives
- shared values&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hierarchy in organizational design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Coordination: Modularity will lead to hierarchy, is one belief. If looked at this broadly, hierarchy is adaptable, evolving and decomposable. You can even use loose coupling which enables things to change swiftly with the general architecture staying the same. Hierarchy will also allow coordination with less interaction (5 people either need 10 interactions between each other or one person with 4 interactions with the others).&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Control: Bureaucracy, administrative hierarchies, have some principles:
- rational-legal authority
- specialization
- hierarchical structure
- coordination and control through rules and standards
- standardized employment rules and norms
- separation of jobs and people
- formalization
Therefor these are often called machine bureaucracies&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are mechanistic and organic forms, in which the organismic form is less formalized, more flexible and multidirectional.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Today we are rethinking hierarchy as the world arround us is changing ever faster which means that it is less predictable and stable, needing less bureaucratic systems.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;designing organizations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;You need to reconcile specialization with coordination and cooperation, which a solution being the hierarchy. How shall this be designed?&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;First, units need to be defined based on:
- common tasks (maintenance department, finance office, quality control)
- products (department story)
- geography (Wal-Mart)
- process&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A basis can be the intensity of interaction. Whereever the most interaction is needed, there should be a unit grouping. Other factors of influence are:
- economies of scale
- economies of utilization
- learning
- standardization of control systems&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;alternative structural forms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The functional structure is often used with single-business firms, where centralization of functions can lead to scale economics, learning and capability building. With growth in size, the groups build their own values, norms and vocabularies and integration and establishment of semi-autonomous profit centers becomes difficult.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The multidivisional structure started with diversification within companies, as they offer the possibility of decentralized decision making. Matrix structure came about with the realisation that coordination needs to happen across functions, products and geographical areas in the end. The matrix structure was adopted a lot during the 1960s and 1970s and there's a figure of the Shell Matrix pre-1996 on page 210 of the book. Looks interesting ;)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Nonhierarchical coordination structures are another thing, something that many companies have experimented with. Here are some:
- project-based organizations (e.g. oil exploration with highly differentiated project for limited time)
- adhocracies (innovation-oriented and organic, no standardization)
- <a href="http://images.google.com/images?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;amp;q=shamrock&amp;amp;sa=N&amp;amp;tab=wi">shamrock</a> organizations (as of Charles Handy, downsized, first-leaf is the tightly integrated professional core, second-leaf outsourced things from manufacturing to payrole, third-leaf temporary or part-time lowly integrated core support)
- Honeycomb organizations (self-organizing groups, like ants' nests, complexity theory, example: <a href="http://harvardbusinessonline.hbsp.harvard.edu/b02/en/files/printable_catalog/hbspcat_14_Social.doc">AES Honeycomb</a>)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Common features of nonhierarchical structures are:
- focus on coordination rather than control
- reliance on mutual adjustment
- individuals have multiple organizational roles&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management System for Coordination and Control&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Four are of primary importance:
- information systems: the ability to supervise depends on the flow of information upwards
- strategic planning systems: whether formal or informal, systematic or ad hoc, it is a strong means of coordination. A strategic plan often includes: a statement of goals,  a set of assumptions or forecasts, a qualitative statement, specific action steps, a set of financial projections
- financial planning and control system
- capital expenditure budget
- the operating budget
- human resource system
- corporate culture as a control mechanism
- integrating different control mechanisms&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
