<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Investing | Oliver Thylmann]]></title>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/categories/investing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-10T11:31:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://thylmann.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oliver Thylmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tripple Stock Play]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/10/08/tripple-stock-play/"/>
    <updated>2007-10-08T06:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/10/08/tripple-stock-play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You need to maximize the value of your portfolio. That is very important. As OnVista was recently sold, with a nice premium, so I made a bit of money on that one. Having worked there, having built up what is now Ligatus, I knew that good things were bound to come out of it. But now they question comes how to maximize the free potential. As I have eBay and Nokia shares and have entrepreneurs and VCs tell me that they read this blog, I opted for the following: I hopped onto eBay and bought a nice Nokia N95. Welcome to portofolio maximization strategies, which also help me possibly do a bit of video blogging ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Facebook Misunderstandings]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/07/14/the-facebook-misunderstandings/"/>
    <updated>2007-07-14T16:38:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/07/14/the-facebook-misunderstandings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People are going back and forth about Facebook but there is one little misconception in the discussions going on. A <a href="http://scobleizer.com/2007/07/12/why-facebook-why-now/">good post comes from Scoble</a> that highlights the good sides of Facebook. And it is really what the ultra pro gang likes to heard. Facebook is amazing, the widgetization will continue, Facebook will grow without end.</p>

<p>I actually don't think anybody tries to deny that. What people are disputing is the valuation part of the entire thing. Valuations on the stock market depend on revenues and profits. Otherwise it is hype, and that is what we had in the first bubble and as soon as that hype entered the normal stock market, real people got hurt because they invested in beliefs.</p>

<p>To take a look at the other side you should read <a href="http://www.watchmojo.com/web/blog/?p=1394">this post</a> which talks about a 2008 IPO. The thing most interesting in there is the calculation that Microsoft promised some revenue to Facebook due to a 2006 deal they did. This might be the source of the main revenue of the $100 million Facebook is talking about as revenues for this year. Google's amazing growth engine has a Price to Sales multiple on the stock market of 14. This means that even at $100 million of revenues, with amazing growth, Facebook shouldn't be more valuable than $1.4 billion now, with growth factored in as in the case of the Google stock price. Now think if Google's expertise and business model is something where you can understand that revenue and profit growth will come. Now think about Facebook. The metrics are not as clear. The upside is good but nobody out there has proven it yet. That's like investing in a start-up and that shouldn't be something unexperienced people do.</p>

<p>This is what some people think is nuts, and I have to admit I am one of them. $8 billion is just too steep, unless somebody buys it that really needs the expertise and entry into the web area and has an amazing sales team to make money of the site. Let's see what happens. I have obviously been wrong before.</p>

<p>&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Of course if they would IPO, then long term it might end up at several billion USD, hence the idea of the IPO. I wouldn't sell either ... but not for the valuation part but simply because Facebook might become a real company with long term potential.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Long Term Investment Strategy]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/07/05/long-term-investment-strategy/"/>
    <updated>2007-07-05T20:01:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/07/05/long-term-investment-strategy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fortune recently had an issue about retiring rich, or at least rich enough to live happily ever after. There were lots of different strategies on how to invest, many by the big investment gurus out there. I have to admit that I read many books that go into great detail on the different strategies by the wise men cited in the stories, and you can learn a great deal by reading the books, only one methodology kind of rang a bell. This is something that Tom Gardner from Motley Fool called <a href="http://money.cnn.com/galleries/2007/fortune/0706/gallery.6trends.fortune/index.html">6 supertrends ... and 6 superstocks</a>.</p>

<p>The idea is to invest in trends that you believe to be true. Real trends that will shape your future life. You can then obviously mix it with trying to find trends that are not really visible yet or possibly trying to find small under covered companies that will grow with this trend.</p>

<p>I have to admit that I was a long time member of <a href="http://fool.com">Motley Fool</a> and followed Tom's and other Fool's posting, also being very active on the boards themselves. The idea that Tom posts about in the Fortune article is something that fits very well with the long term strategy that Motley Fool is advocating. This really led to my believe that the stock market is something you can invest in, but not something you can play with. Going in and out of stocks in hourly trades or even monthly trades is nothing for me.</p>

<p>So what kind of stocks did I pick in terms of long term trends?</p>

<p>&lt;strong&gt;eBay&lt;/strong&gt;: The company has a relatively secure main business that has still lots of room for growth. Due to the volume of auctions eBay is very hard to replace and same as Google's profits are growing via optimization, I believe eBay still has a lot of room to grow through usability improvements and moving into other closely tied spaces. One of the big reasons was also their real banking on APIs and that those can be free and eBay still makes more money. That trend will continue for a long time.</p>

<p>Above that I do really believe in PayPal. It's a bank that belongs to eBay and there are some very fine long term numbers playing in their favor. I expect a lot more on that front. Payment on the internet is a way forward and eBay is very well set up with PayPal.</p>

<p>Third Skype. Maybe they did pay a lot but again it is the &quot;all my friends are there&quot; phenomenon that will keep you locked in and with additional features and easier integration through their API knowledge, moves into the services market, direct local connections and the like, I believe that it can be a real winner.</p>

<p>It's really three trends that play in eBays favor, a favor that will make it outperform the market in the long run.</p>

<p>&lt;strong&gt;Nokia&lt;/strong&gt;: I probably invested too much during the first bubble here but am back well in the green. Sure they are having problems press wise in the high end with stuff like the iPhone but boy do these people know mobility. This does not mean that you hype everything, but with a paying suppliers later than getting their money, banking on platforms like cars, investing in Symbian as an OS, covering the entire spectrum from low to high end and still trying out new things like a tablet, blogging and more, I believe that if you believe that mobility is here to stay, and that we will be more mobile in the future, and that a very big opportunity is in 3rd world countries, then Nokia is the company to bank on. Sure a Motorola can have a one time Razr success, and sure others are making money on licenses. But I don't know licensing, but I do know that Nokia will always be very good.</p>

<p>&lt;strong&gt;F5 Networks&lt;/strong&gt;: Will we have more traffic on the internet in the future? Will there be more big web sites? Will there be more huge web sites? Will there be more encrypted traffic? Do companies want to buy something where they have somebody big to blame? Are they a if not the leader in load balancing, world wide load balancing, ssl accelerators, ... and have they been small when I invested several years ago and undercovered? Hell yes! The stock performance tells the tale.</p>

<p>&lt;strong&gt;Apple&lt;/strong&gt;: Buy the stuff you use. This is one of the cases where you just need to look around yourself. I am now up close to 300%, one of my better performers, and I believe that they will have a good future ahead of them. The thing is that design is a very important thing. Once things just work, design is really one of the very few things that will make your product stand out. And I always wanted a Mac. Suddenly Jobs came back and the Mac Laptops were not too expensive anymore. The iPod was the second hard disk mp3 player I bought and it was such a leap forward, just for the design and want to have factor.</p>

<p>They really know how to build great products, how to excel, how to really thrill people. The thing is that this is how the future of marketing will work. Sure you can market everything, but if you invest half of the money you want to spend on marketing into product development and get the product right, then the rest of the marketing budget will have a much bigger effect. This is what Apple has understood.</p>

<p>&lt;strong&gt;Genentech&lt;/strong&gt;: Is medicine a research business? Is/Was Genentech still rather small? Yes, it was when I invested and I just felt that they are attracting the right people to be successful in the long run. Because in the end the right drugs need a good development team and a good research effort. This is what Genentech really excells at it seems. I have no way of looking at a drug pipeline and finding out which drug will make it and which won't and how much money each can make, and factor that in. I think in the long run, looking at other companies, Genentech is bound to have some really killers out there. This is why I invested there next to a fund by Sal. Oppenheim that is managed together with several consulting companies in the medical business. The fund is really my general bet thinking that if several consultants decide on something, they can't be all wrong (and history up till now has proven that idea right) and above that I have a bit of upside (I believe my long term downside to be limited) with Genentech.</p>

<p>Conclusion. I could be all wrong, but holding those for several years, buying in down time when I did not see the trend changing and still believing in management, up till now has been a good thing for me. Let's see how they look after the second time the stock market tanks and comes back up again. I can't play the market anyway, so I'll just sit it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Money comes around day]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/03/26/money-comes-around-day/"/>
    <updated>2007-03-26T19:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/03/26/money-comes-around-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here in Germany there seems to be a little money day today. First of all, congratulations to the friends from <a href="http://sevenload.de">Sevenload</a> for having closed with <a href="http://www.burdadigital.de/ventures/strategie.html">Burda Digital Ventures</a>.  A great partner for Sevenload, and with mother Burda, one that truly works had to understand where the world is going! And as <a href="http://lumma.de/eintrag.php?id=3346">Nico already put it</a>,  this means that <a href="http://hebig.com/">Heiko</a> might come by Cologne a bit more often. :) Here is the <a href="http://blog.sevenload.de/2007/03/26/burda-digital-ventures-ist-unser-neuer-starker-partner/">official blog post.</a></p>

<p>It seems that the big media companies really want to make sure that they have their own stakes in the growing video market on the internet. It will be really interesting to see how all of this turn out. The biggest an most interesting thing with all of this is really cost, and I can only suggest reading the last posts from <a href="http://www.pbs.org/cringely/">Cringely</a>. The thing is that each new viewer ads costs, and if you go with a P2P system, there is a lag involved, it only works with highly popular files and the cost is really with the ISP which they will surely not like. Check out <a href="http://www.pbs.org/cringely/pulpit/2007/pulpit_20070315_001831.html">this post</a> by Cringely to see another option: <a href="http://neokast.com/">Neokast</a>. Read the blog :)</p>

<p>Next up is <a href="http://blog.openbc.com/2007/03/econozco_joins_.html">eConozco joins OpenBC</a>. With the acquisition of the leading spanish social network (ok, Orkut seems to be really big in Brazil with like 20 million members, ... no spain, but ok... never mind) they want to push further into their internationalization.</p>

<p>The most interesting thing is actually Experteer. It all started with me watching the interview with <a href="http://www.gruenderszene.de/?p=101">Martin Weber on Gründerszene</a> today. I can only agree with Lukasz that <a href="http://www.holtzbrinck-ventures.com/index.php?de">Holtzbrinck Ventures</a> is one of the best, and/or most active, VCs in Germany at the moment. Truyl a great team. The interesting thing is that in the interview Martin Weber talks about <a href="http://www.experteer.de/">Experteer</a> (min 7:56), which they founded 6 months ago. It's fully built on Ruby on Rails it seems (looking forward to seeing another scaling proof) and a little bit different take on the recruitment market. In Experteer you as a user pay to become member, and Headhunters and companies can pitch 60.000 EUR plus jobs to you.  Interesting. Even more interesting, now Christian posts that <a href="http://blogging.vc/2007/03/bv-capital-leads-investment-in-german-experteerde">BV Capital and Wellington Partners have invested</a>!</p>

<p>Now I don't personally know the team behind Experteer, but with the investor team now behind them, I am looking forward to seeing a good growth curve. :)</p>

<p>So we have Xing buying stuff, Sevenload getting big cash to extend video with Burda, and then the young Experteer getting money from the big guys. This round goes to Experteer I'd say. Looking forward to what happens next.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I won the alarm:clock euro quiz]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/03/06/i-won-the-alarm-clock-euro-quiz/"/>
    <updated>2007-03-06T09:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2007/03/06/i-won-the-alarm-clock-euro-quiz</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wohoo! <a href="http://www.thealarmclock.com/euro/">alarm:clock euro</a> had a <a href="http://www.thealarmclock.com/euro/archives/2007/03/alarmclock_euro_puzz_16.html">quiz</a> again recently in which they asked to name the VC firm founder who made his first fortune in modems and fax cards. As a hint they added that the firm is now on its third and largest fund. Having run around in the venture scene a bit in the last few months, I obviously knew that they ment Dr. Gottfried Neuhaus from Neuhaus Partners in Hamburg. Also knowing Valerie form alarm:clock I had to quickly write the answer over to them and hey, I was the first! You can now see my wonderful picture right <a href="http://www.thealarmclock.com/euro/archives/2007/03/alarmclock_euro_puzz_17.html">here</a>.</p>

<p>A good distraction coming in the office in the morning ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
