<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Advertising | Oliver Thylmann]]></title>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/categories/advertising/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-10T11:31:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://thylmann.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oliver Thylmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sorry for not blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/11/28/sorry-for-not-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-28T21:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/11/28/sorry-for-not-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been over 2 months since my last post and this is inexcussable. But if you check the right side of this blog you will see some posts from <a href="http://stuff.thylmann.net">stuff.thylmann.net</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/olivert">twitter.com/olivert</a> and <a href="http://delicious.com/othylmann">delicious.com/othylmann</a> which are no deep thoughts, but might give you an overview of what I am reading and thinking about.</p>

<p>For the most part this thinking revolves around <a href="http://adcloud.net/">Adcloud</a>, a second project we just started at Ormigo which is currently generating a lot of buzz and is leading to some very interesting discussions. In very short terms, we are extracting the performance advertising ad server system from Ormigo and making it into it's own product, creating, through a few more features, an open performance advertising exchange.</p>

<p>Sounds a bit abstract for now, but I will try to get into it a bit more deeply as things go on. We are truely leveraging our experience with agile development to get new releases out quickly and are working very closely with our customers to get the right stuff in there first.</p>

<p>But these are busy times so please excuse me for a bit more lighter blogging at this time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Digital Disruption]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/08/15/on-digital-disruption/"/>
    <updated>2008-08-15T07:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/08/15/on-digital-disruption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I believe in digital disruption and I do believe there is a lot that will change, but who am I telling that to my readers. I rarely blog about a blog but now Simon Waldman <a href="http://www.simonwaldman.net/2008/08/14/my-new-blog-digital-disruption/">started</a> a new one entitled: &quot;<a href="http://digitaldisruption.wordpress.com/">Digital Disruption</a>&quot; and it's a great read, especially because it is from inside the fense. Simon is Director of Digital Strategy and Development at the Guardian Media Group.</p>

<p>Just read <a href="http://digitaldisruption.wordpress.com/2008/08/14/the-outsider-solution-chuck-away-your-businesswrong-wrong-wrong/">The Outsider Solution</a>, or <a href="http://digitaldisruption.wordpress.com/2008/08/13/margins-dividends-topline-growth/">post on the NYT</a>. Having met Simon some time ago I can only suggest reading the blog. He does get it as they say, and not only from a &quot;let's go all digital&quot; point of view but from a real understanding of the newspaper business, with lots of discussions with all involved.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Online Advertising gets a new name: Google]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/08/07/online-advertising-gets-a-new-name-google/"/>
    <updated>2008-08-07T19:14:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/08/07/online-advertising-gets-a-new-name-google</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We all know Google is big, but today a few things popped up that should be shaking the media industry in its very foundation. Sadly, I doubt that will happen, partly because the media industry is profit focussed and partly because it does not really know what its core competence is.</p>

<p>Jason Calacanis recently sent out an email in relation to Google starting Knol entitled &quot;Is Google a content company?&quot; This included one nice list:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Let's run a test: what is the role of a content publisher?</p>

<ol>
<li>Secure talent</li>
<li>Distribute their work</li>
<li>Monetize that work</li>
<li>Pay the content creator for their work</li>
<li>Build a library of that work for future monetization&lt;/blockquote&gt;
If we can roughly agree that this is correct, then Google is a content company, at least with Knol, but possibly even because of the simple fact that many blogs are using AdSense. And if you look at some bigger publisher you are somebody wondering if Google didn't secure their talent in an AdSense deal, is distributing their work via Google, monetizing it via AdSense, paying them a share and indexing the work for future monetization.</li>
</ol>


<p>So all in all, Google is becoming a publisher.</p>

<p>Obviously, next up is advertising, the monetization part. Google came to the monetization of search via text links by accident and largely copied Overture. And now with Knol, they are trying to monetize more of the second clicks, which is actually similar in AdSense. If people don't click on an AdSense link right away, then let them do it in the second click. Of course it was all performance driven but that let out the branding part of the business.</p>

<p>Then Google bought Doubleclick and boy is the strategy amazing. Their Adsense covers the smaller 100k visitors sites and Doubleclick covers the rest. Just <a href="http://www.attributor.com/blog/get-your-fair-share-of-the-ad-network-pie/">check this Attributor post</a>. It's scary.</p>

<p>Today Google announced <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2008/08/new-enhancements-on-google-content.html">a few new additions to their content network</a> ... like Frequency Capping, which <a href="http://plentyoffish.wordpress.com/2008/08/07/googles-to-dominate-display-ads/">Plentyoffish is all happy about</a>, understandably so, and argues that it will make Google dominate display ads. I personally think the last two points are the scary ones:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;</p>

<pre><code>&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span style=&amp;quot;font-weight: bold;&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Improved Ads Quality:&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt; Brings performance improvements within the Google content network.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span style=&amp;quot;font-weight: bold;&amp;quot;&amp;gt;View-Through Conversions&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;: Enables advertisers to gain insights on how many users visited their sites after seeing an ad. This helps advertisers determine the best places to advertise so users will see more relevant ads.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
</code></pre>

<p>&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
As a short background, what Google now does is serve a Doubleclick Cookie with each AdSense ad request, effectively creating one big cookie/profiling network over all Doubleclick and AdSense instances. But what are Doubleclick instances? Those are actually way more than the publisher installations DFP (Dart for Publishers) but also DFA (Dart for Advertisers). So an Agency like Pilot might run a DFA instance and use it to track AdImpressions of bookings they had, clicks as well as conversions. And this is where the scary part is. Those agencies will be able to (with a few twists) book directly into any AdSense placement that has image ads enabled. And they have a cookie about the user that clicks through having booked an Ad on a big publisher. Run a Frequency Capping campaign on a few of the biggest publishers out there where the audience is that you believe to want to attract, cookieing the user, then targeting them on AdSense. This model might still be a few days out but this is where this is going. At least, I have not heard yet that there will be no cookie sharing from DFA and DFP instances.</p>

<p>And on the other side, there are a lot of players out there that generate leads through Google's clicks. This is a huge market, I know, and you know what... Google is going there too. Check out <a href="http://www.lorm.de/2008/08/07/google-merchant-search-beta/">Google Merchant Search Beta</a>, where Google is generating leads (possibly even sales, because they don't say how the billing works) for credit institutes. Damn god.</p>

<p>Google is simply using their vast data pool to <a href="http://weblogs.hitwise.com/us-heather-hopkins/2008/07/google_lively_predictions_goog.html">take a look at what to launch next</a>. By now they are becoming a publisher, pushing further into advertising in both directions (clicks to leads and clicks to branding) and using their vast data pool to become more of the web. Bummer.</p>

<p>I see that many people out there do not want Google to become online Advertising but I am not sure if their &quot;don't want to&quot; is linked to some strategy that is filtered through to the profit centers having no option but to use Google.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yahoo has given up to Google]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/06/13/yahoo-has-given-up-to-google/"/>
    <updated>2008-06-13T20:26:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/06/13/yahoo-has-given-up-to-google</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As sad as it is, Yahoo! has given up and Google is now running ads within Yahoo!. Check Michael's post here entitled <a href="http://www.techcrunch.com/2008/06/13/massive-destruction-of-shareholder-value-employee-morale-and-internet-health/">Massive Destruction of Shareholder Value</a> for some good thoughts and links. The thing is that this is actually bad for almost everyone. For example, Google is monetizing better than others because they have more inventory, and more advertisers and more inventory advertisers invent. advert. i.a. .... As Steve Balmer said, the Flywheel is just bigger. So the advertisers are paying more to buy ads within Google. So now for a search result within Yahoo! for the term &quot;Insurance&quot; you can either buy it cheap on Yahoo! or expensive on Google and in the end, it will be the same click, with Yahoo! probably opting to choosing the expensive one.</p>

<p>Of course, Yahoo! will make more money in the short term, but in the long term that money will move to Google, and their Flywheel will get a size that is just too big to replace. We are almost there, but I still believe there are options to build something truely open that leverages the power of the internet. With the deal being non-exclusive, and Yahoo! being able to mix and match as they choose, the deal is a bit more open but the internet can go bigger than that. There is a nice thing that Eric Schmidt <a href="http://www.techcrunch.com/2008/06/12/yahoo-runs-into-googles-arms/">said</a>:</p>

<p>&lt;em&gt;If there were an issue, it’s perfectly possible that you can do commercial deals that look like outsourcing deals which are not exclusive and where industry structures allow everybody to win. If you look in the automobile industry and lots and lots of industries like that, you have suppliers who supply other people. So if there were a deal, it would be based on those sorts of principles.&lt;/em&gt;</p>

<p>The thing is that the example just does not hold under analysis. I know somebody working in the part-supplier industry, and yes, by now some car manufacturers are actually buying from different providers just so there will still be 3 different ones at least. That alone would be like Yahoo! buying from Google and X and Y to make sure competition remains high. They don't, but help create a monopoly, something that automobile industry would make sure to not have happen. But there is another difference. This is more like Mercedes outsourcing the sales of their cars to a 3rd party. Above that, these cars cannot be stored, but fall of a cliff and die if not sold when created, and with each car your sell (not produce) you gain a bit of knowledge how to sell better. Your short term goal is to let the best seller sell your cars, but your long term goal would be to become the best seller of your cars. Otherwise, sooner or later in that model you become the parts provider where the seller knows your exact cost structure and will make sure you produce content the cheapest possible. Because if you can't sell your cars yourselves, you depend on Google to do it for you ... or ads in this respect.</p>

<p>Of course we can presume that giving it all to Google will result in highest prices and best system for all, but that's just not have this economic model of ours works. Believe me, I do believe in Google's performance marketing model and actually believe even CPM ads should be performance based, but that's another subject. The problem is this moves us more into a monopoly and somebody needs to start thinking strategy please, and long term, because short term strategy will default to Google at this point, or to someobdy else that will ultimately be there to market your site for you.</p>

<p>Google actually has <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2008/06/our-agreement-to-provide-ad-technology.html">something to say</a> about all of this. Of course this is a not a merger, which is a good thing, but if it results in Google becoming the sole provider of search advertising, then emm... who cares. Google says this does not remove a player from the field, but this is untrue if the investors and management in Yahoo! are thinking short term, because then they do not have an incentive to keep improving and innovating in search advertising (and content advertising which is really what Google is moving to next, all performance based). Yes, Yahoo! can do similar arrangements with others, but who would those others be? If Yahoo! is not doing all of this to make more money, then I am lost, and there is nobody else that would allow Yahoo! to make more money, because there is nobody yet who has applied performance based advertising to an entire property, even though Yahoo! is close to that. But as said, there are no others. And yes, this does not let Google raise prices for advertisers, ... but as detailed above, again, who cares.</p>

<p>So this is a lot more dangerous then some make it out to be. We need a real strategy, we need some bold steps, we need a Linux of Advertising actually.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ad Networks 1999 and Today]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/04/03/ad-networks-1999-and-today/"/>
    <updated>2008-04-03T19:24:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2008/04/03/ad-networks-1999-and-today</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two blog posts got me back on a certain subject I thought I'd write about again. First of all, Mark Cuban posted &quot;<a href="http://www.blogmaverick.com/2008/04/03/i-couldnt-resist/">I couldn't resist ... Youtube vs. Broadcast.com 10 years ago</a>&quot; in which he compares YouTube and Broadcast.com. Yes it is not a 100% comparison, but interesting none the less. Then I found &quot;<a href="http://mathewingram.com/media/2008/03/24/ad-networks-inventory-vs-the-brand/">Ad Networks: Inventory vs. the brand</a>&quot; by Mathew Ingram (via <a href="http://www.simonwaldman.net/2008/04/03/links-for-2008-04-03/">Simon</a>). From that post just see this part from the end:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Maybe it’s just the spillover from the sub-prime mortgage meltdown, but in some cases packaging remnant inventory and selling it through an ad network reminds me of the Wall Street practice of bundling underperforming or questionable mortgages together, and “securitizing” them in order to unload them onto outside investors. That kind of strategy works really well — right up until it doesn’t.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Back in the first bubble I was running a statistics service for webmasters and we were using Flycast, which very soon folded because that network kind of did not work. Next up for us was <a href="http://tribalfusion.com/">Tribalfusion</a>, and they survived. One of the features I really liked about them was that I could put ads into their system on my site myself for free. Very cool indeed. Seems a bit like Google's AdManager today. Then there was Doubleclick for the big sites, which was not just a service to use and pay for as a publisher or agency, but a real network selling your inventory, until they stopped doing it when the marketing money ran out. So we had networks, and we had targeting, and we had lots of reach and bundling over different bigger sites.</p>

<p>I do believe that we are running down a similar road and we'll see if lots of those networks out there will survive today. There is a lot more reach out there of course but one of the biggest differences we have is that the cost side has really really changed. You can have more server power and reach for stuff like behavioral targeting and costs for ad servers has gone way down, as has bandwidth. This allows both better targeting and and created networks that can run on the unsold inventory, because even with several cents CPM you can still run profitably. Also there are more real marketing dollars out there obviously.</p>

<p>Sadly the latter gave rise to ads that are not something you want on your site. The thing is that often times, cheesy ads that have higher click throughs to worse conversion but yield higher ecpms in the end. That is why you have these weird flashing banners, or texts that are totally unreasonable like &quot;You are the 1.000.000th Visitor and you Won!&quot;</p>

<p>As always these are interesting times, and I 100% believe in networks with a clear focus, as I wouldn't run one otherwise. But we are focusing on filling inventory with marketing budgets from small local players in a performance marketing manner, making you other money. Others allow for exploiting your inventory through behavioral targeting techniques, making you more money. Still others are bundling smaller sites, who are allowing them to make money at all. All have to watch out what they stand for and that they are really providing value over and beyond the other solutions out there. And all have to make sure they can compete with Google, on which ever level that is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
