<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 2 | Oliver Thylmann]]></title>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/categories/2/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-10T11:31:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://thylmann.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oliver Thylmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2.10 Managing for Innovation]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-10-managing-for-innovation/"/>
    <updated>2003-05-05T09:44:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-10-managing-for-innovation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;Invention: coming up with a new idea
Innovation: coming up with a new application of an idea</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>Innovations can happen both in the product (new braking system, new hotel check-out service) or the process (new way to make them, new way to match customer with available rooms). The boundary is often blurred.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Pull innovation happens in response to customers needs while push innovations happen as a result of advances and speculative development. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The greatest portion of those developments is incremental but sometimes radical ones are needed.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are several barriers and enablers to innovation.
-   Knowledge brokering is about helping people with a problem to become aware of the idea that might help. Knowledge brokers capture good ideas, keep them alive, imagine new uses for them and put promising concepts to the test.
-   Managing for creativity is about creating new knowledge, maximizing employee’s creativity which is a function of expertise, creative thinking skills and motivation. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Managers have most control about the motivations part. The thing about motivation is that if you enable intrinsic motivation (the desire to perform actions because the action is rewarded) people will walk around and find more things than based on extrinsic motivation (the incentive is external to the action). &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Based on Amabile’s research there are sex important supports for motivation in encouraging creativity:
-   Challenge (a task that stretches you)
-   Freedom (in the choice of means, not the choice of ends, which can be argued but this is the idea)
-   Resources (e.g. time)
-   Workgroup features (mutual supportive with different expertise, experience)
-   Supervisory encouragement
-   Organisational support&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Incubating ideas in relation to ideas is important, meaning to let them develop a bit in the subconscious. People sometimes need to be idle, let the mind flow.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Barrier to innovation can be resources but other examples include:
-   People working in narrow boxes
-   Fear of failure (see entrepreneurship in the US versus Europe)
-   Lack of rewards
-   Hoarding of the best people
-   Too much bureaucracy
-   Not-invented-here attitude
-   Poor Communications
-   Sticking to a successful product
-   Business-as-usual preference
-   Short-term thinking&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Different organisations will favour different approaches. For further information on this see page 14. In general this might be to focus on social-external (inter-firm collaboration, supplier involvement, closeness to the customer, …), Social-internal (Planned process, cross-functional teams, use of intranets, …), Individual-external (Networking) or Individual-internal (Hero innovator, Air cover for mavericks, skunkworks, …) methods. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The implications of this is that you might need to allow considerable freedom to some people (hero innovators), create a liberal corporate culture or a clear R&amp;D unit, decide what kind of secrecy you want your plans to have and have a clear managerial perception on the importance of innovation.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Some people say that customers should be included in the design process, sometimes called “Lead User Research”, which relies on identifying individuals or organisations that are ahead of their market segment. These might be:
-   Target market leader users who used prototypes they sometimes developed themselves
-   Analogous market lead users who come from fields with similar applications (racing for car brakes)
-   Attribute lead users&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2.9 The design of new products, processes and services]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-9-the-design-of-new-products-processes-and-services/"/>
    <updated>2003-05-05T09:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-9-the-design-of-new-products-processes-and-services</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;Here, design should be seen from an operations perspective. Ideas can come from customers, competitors, staff or R&amp;D and they can be classified as:
-   Market-pull (wants and needs of customers, ideas can find a ready market)
-   Technology-push (uses for unexploited technological solutions)</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>There are several stages in the design process:
1.  Idea generation
2.  Screening (to reduce ideas to manageable number, use market research, financial implications, operations capabilities)
3.  Preliminary design (for enough for a prototype)
4.  Evaluation and improvement (before testing in the market)
5.  Prototyping and final design (visualise how manufacturing process works, pilot offerings)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There is a big different between the Japanese and the Western approach to design. Time-to-Market is often crucial, especially in rapidly changing markets, and Japan is partly successful because they have a constant stream of new models based on multi-functional team work (e.g. Sony Clies). The idea is constantly exchanged between players in different departments (“simultaneous engineering”) (example given of Sony Walkman, with one person pushing the product through because of belief that it will succeed.)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The Western approach is more of a relay race where things are passed from department to department with their own priorities which results in departments not looking into problems or opportunities that might show somewhere else. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The process design is about making the new product/service available in a way that satisfies all relevant stakeholders. Process types look at volume and variety of the output which results in 5 process types, namely:
-   Project (low, one of a kind volume and highly customized, large IT projects)
-   Jobbing (letterhead design)
-   Batch (commercial bakery)
-   Mass (electrical billing operations)
-   Continuous (highly standardized and high volume, petrochemicals).&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;To choose a process type one needs to consider what moving off the above diagonal means. You might be too standardized/customized for your volume level or invest too little in technology for your volume based on your standardization.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;For service process types might look more at degree of customization and labour intensiveness instead of volume:
-   Professional service (highly trained specialists)
-   Service shops (trained specialists, universities, travel shops)
-   Mass services (banks, supermarkets)
-   Service factories (little interaction between customer and provider)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Another important part is the layout (arrangement of physical facilities) and flow (how things move through the operations system).
-   Fixed layout: one position for all tasks, difficult to schedule, associated with projects e.g. construction, music festivals
-   Process (functional) layout: arrangements according to common process, high flexibility and interesting work but difficult to control, low utilisation and high work-in-progress; e.g. school
-   Cell layout: type of products are grouped, high throughput but still interesting; e.g. factories, cafeterias
-   Product layout: in order of the stages of the product, lowest unit-cost in high volume, use of specialised equipment, very repetitive; e.g. car assembly plant&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;To choose the appropriate layout you need to consider:
-   cost and flexibility of the process
-   time and distance that materials and customers travel in the process
-   flow of materials, information and customers through the operation&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Finding the best way requires finding the most efficient linked-up materials flow. In general, the order of layouts can be seen as correlated with process types (project – fixed; continuous – product)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In a process-focused operation there will be a flexibility in the flow to allow for customized products (users can find their own way through the supermarket) while in product-focused operations a standardised output for the lowest possible cost is produced like an assembly line where the product takes a pre-defined route. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Operations design has a human and technological side and questions like:
-   how should the jobs be designed?
-   What technologies should be used in the process?
-   What will the role of the customers be in the process?
Need to be asked. Automations and worker skill are adversely correlated.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;In job design look at which tasks, sequence, location, interaction, autonomy and skills are needed. Scientific management might work best in things like call centres, fast-food restaurants and theme parks while in other places more empowerment might be needed. Something called the socio-technical systems approach tries to balance the interested of the operation with those of the works, trying systems like autonomous work groups, direct responsibility, cross-training and involvement.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Work measurement is there to analyse the processes to identify delays, stoppages, wasted times and in general steps that do not add value. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;As a product moves through it’s lifecycle most innovation will first come from product innovations while later they will come from process innovations. Lots of work has been moved away from humans to be performed by machines, automated. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;When choosing a technology Slack et al. suggest looking at three dimensions:
-   degree of automation (are people required to operate it; high: greater reliability, faster processing; low: great flexibility, customization)
-   scale (processing capacity; high: lower unit costs, better capacity utilisation)
-   degree of integration (does it form an integrated system between different technologies; high: faster throughput; low: greater mix and volume flexibility)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;It should be remembered that all change carriers risk from safe if you change neither product nor process to high risk if you change both at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2.8 Marketing Innovation]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-8-marketing-innovation/"/>
    <updated>2003-05-05T09:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-8-marketing-innovation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;Innovation can occur organisational or in a product or process. Things change and this leads to the need of new product/service development (NPD/NSD) even if only to update the solution for a cycle extension. Generally, new products in new markets make only up 10% of the new products. 20% are targeted to old markets and 50%+ are mere updates. It’s the plodding (steadily regenerated) cash cow that continues to dominate development processes in most markets.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>Innovation falls into several categories.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous innovation is typical for fast-moving consumer goods (FMCG) markets (e.g. washing powder). There are regular innovations here without the need of new customer behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Companies need to develop their existing products within a changing competitive environment. Here you need to look at something called position drift, which can be shown in a position map, normally a 4 quadrant map with 4 different attributes (for segmentation of the market) on the sides (e.g. basic-luxurious and expensive-economical) which enable the placement of products within these 4 quadrants and further group them in segments (circles within the map).&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;These attributes (also called dimension) can be found through factor analysis which looks at the factors of a company’s value proposition and ranks them in order of importance to the customer, not the supplier or anyone else, but clearly the customer, through the customer’s eyes. Cluster analysis can then be used to create segments (clusters of customers with similar expectations). Often market research is used here.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Once you found your segment, the center of this segment is the idea product or service for that segment. This is where the drift comes in.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Customer drift: customers’ demands change, the center moves and the cluster size may change.
Competitor drift: competitors change their position and your competitive advantage is reduced. This is especially problematic if one product should fill several segments and then a competitor moves into the center of one of those segments. (a good place is between your competitor and the ideal)
Ego drift: One of the most relevant shifts, where a brand manager or development team reposition their own brand to a less than optimal position.  (e.g. Coca Cola’s try with a new image and taste because they thought something new was needed)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;That means that those position maps need to be updated frequently and sometimes changes in the environment require a radical shift to a totally new segment. Charities got a problem when the national lottery enabled people to feel that they were giving to charity (25%) while having a chance of winning (50%, 25% goes to the operator and government).&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;To reach your long-term product objectives you need a product strategy and there are said to be basically 4 different strategies for growth in volume and profit seen in the Ansoff Matrix&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Market penetration
Existing products in existing markets (most NPDs go here)
-   increasing sales to existing customers
-   finding new customers
It’s about persuading a customer to buy more of a product either by taking away from another one or by getting people to increase their usage. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Product development
New products in existing markets (traditional NPDs)
Use an existing brand name and extend it into neighbouring fields, called brand extension (e.g. American Express moving into travel, banking, private healthcare, theatre booking, …, Coca-Cola with Diet Coke)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Market development
New products in existing markets
This is about finding new uses for existing products like new geographical areas. &lt;br /&gt;
Diversification
New products in new markets
Concentric diversification: when there is a link between the new and old activities
Conglomerate diversification: completely new, sometimes buying a company with the required expertise. The further you move from the home market, the higher the risk.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are different approaches here like a rational plan, communication web and disciplined problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Dynamically continuous innovations are significant and require some adaptation by the consumer, e.g. CD-Roms for home computer. In general, this happens in markets that are used to change, like IT.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The changes here need to be inline with the strategy or the strategy needs to be changed. Sony creates around 1000 new products a year, with 200 aimed at new markets. You need to review:&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Production capabilities (is skill and firmware there)
Financial performance (affordability of changes, profits and cash flow)
Cannibalism (how much business will come from existing brands)
Match with existing ranges (if complimentary then they are easier to sell, existing distribution patterns)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;There are different innovation processes. These might involve regular meetings (formal and informal), brainstorming, formal R&amp;D programs, valuation/identification of the market or a suggestion scheme. Ideas come from every direction, sometimes from unlikely places and an organisations capability to innovate is ‘intangible capital’. Scanning the environment and keeping an open mind is important.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Customer innovation is the greatest source of new ideas. Focus on the customer, listen attentively and use things like employee suggestion schemes. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Innovation imitation, meaning to copy, is another big thing. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Discontinuous innovation (Disruptive technologies?) is rare, totally new, requires a complete change in consumer behaviour, like the first appearance of video recorders. Many products are launched without real research, gap analysis can help here to find possible gaps to fill.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Usage gap = Market potential – Existing usage (most important for brand leaders with more than 30% of the market, looking to expand that market)
Access gap = limits in availability, maximize distribution (not easy)
Product or service gap = part of the market a company is excluded from due to product characteristics
Competitive gap = results from your competitive performance
(Market gap analysis could be used the same way to look at gaps in the market instead of the product.)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The development process is often unpredictable and management tries to minimise the risk with organisation’s corporate and marketing strategies being a guideline for the screening process. In Japan, they have less R&amp;D costs, bring products to market faster and even try them out directly in the market.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;More than 80% of ideas of new products fail and for mass markets a concept test is used to assess customer reactions (market research or pilot program). Between the idea and the launch lies product development and market research is needed to find out if what you are trying to build is really what you need. Once there is a workable product you still need to test it on customers and these tests can be used to alter the product a bit. For services, this is often not a good solution but you rather launch in a make or break sense. Test marketing is used to optimize the marketing mix prior to launch.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;(Page 37 has a very detailed figure for service development)&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2.7 A Strategic view of performance]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-7-a-strategic-view-of-performance/"/>
    <updated>2003-05-05T09:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-7-a-strategic-view-of-performance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;p&gt;Strategy is the pattern of activities followed by an organisation in pursuit of its long-term purposes.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<p>Organisational purposes are often tacit rather than clearly articulated (Comment: In Japan these seem to be clear and help people to move in the right direction.). Common purposes include:
-   profitability (sometimes equal weight to cash-flow)
-   growth
-   shareholder value
-   customer satisfaction&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A wider range of stakeholders need to be taken into account which is reflected in the BSC. Organisation need to serve the interests of multiple stakeholder groups simultaneously. Some of these groups might have conflicting objectives.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;The Market-based approach to strategy looks at the near environment where companies compete for customers, suppliers, resources and also compete to influence external factors. In the end you want to have a competitive advantage. This is where Porter’s five forces framework comes from which suggests that there are five types of competitive pressure.
1.  Industry competitors (rivalry among existing firms)
2.  Potential entrants (a barrier of entry is important here)
3.  Bargaining power of buyers
4.  Bargaining power of suppliers (if lots of suppliers are there, the buyer can put pressure on them for lowest cost)
5.  Threat of substitute products or services&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Porter argues that 1 depends on the importance of 2-5 within your industry. The system can be used to find a sector where an organisation can place itself competitively but it should be remembered that the environment changes over time. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Public-sector organisations can likely better use David McKevitt’s adaptation of the model looking at:
-   Related street-level public organisations
-   Suppliers
-   Professional associations (standards, career ladders)
-   Central government (Politicians, Treasury, Auditors)
-   Client-citizen
All influencing the Street-level public organisation (SLPO)&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;As the environment is not static, based on the above, your strategy should be changing too (your mission sits above that). In general, all this requires a lot of information flow. &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Another approach is the resource-based approach to strategy which focuses on understanding the organisational distinct capabilities in their market with relationships to different stakeholders. In this case, strategy is about choosing among and committing to long-term paths of capability development.  &lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Resources (Human, Tangible, Intangible) enable organisational capabilities and strategy, fed by the industry key success factors, enables a competitive advantage. This competitive advantage has a number of properties:
-   Inimitability
-   Durability
-   Relevance
-   Appropriability&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;John Kay identified 3 main classes of organisational capabilities that have these characteristics: Innovation, Architecture and Reputation.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Strategy now has to build relevant, inimitable, durable and appropriable capabilities while keeping in mind their environment as well as their total value chain, which tells you what the organisation does and in what order. A different way of doing things might create a notable competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;Value chain analysis then looks at:
-   identifying the costs of each activity
-   what factors drive those costs
-   benchmarking
-   understand linkages and horizontal strategy opportunities&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;This analysis then enables finding where distinctive capabilities are based which give rise of core competencies. This might help in finding out what should be done, and what should be outsourced.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;A strategy planning process might then include both the analysis of the near environment, as well as of capabilities and resources to identify alternatives for a new strategy. Normally this happens not very orderly and is only later ordered into a clear plan. In that sense, middle managers are very important as they shape the implementation of a new strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2.6 Cash - The lifeblood of organisations (2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-6-cash-the-lifeblood-of-organisations-2/"/>
    <updated>2003-05-05T09:41:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2003/05/05/2-dot-6-cash-the-lifeblood-of-organisations-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a case study about Weatherfield Community Services, a non-profit organisation that provides meals and home-help services for the elderly in their own homes. They got a new accountant and all really seemed fine. Then the company financials suddenly deteriorated. There are some things that one should be looking at when looking at the financials of a company.</p>

<p>&lt;!-- more --&gt;</p>

<ol>
<li>Look at the rate of expansion in different areas</li>
<li>Calculate ROCE = surplus / average of opening and closing accumulated fund balanced</li>
<li>Look at cash-flow and look at potential problems in management of long and short-term dept/overdrafts.</li>
<li>Look for out of the ordinary expense increases in relation to income/orders</li>
<li>Calculated use of fixed assets via turnover ratios = total annual incoming resources / Annual average fixed assets</li>
<li>Look at working capital</li>
<li>Look at debtors/creditors situation</li>
</ol>


<p>Some interesting things that came up in this case study:
-   when expanding, don’t use an overdraft but get long-term loans for long-term investments
-   even though you are profitable, you might be a take over target with a bad financial status</p>

<p>Questions you always need to ask: How did this happen? How will it not happen again?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
