<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Learning | Oliver Thylmann]]></title>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thylmann.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-10T11:31:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://thylmann.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oliver Thylmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview with the man behind GTD]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/10/14/interview-with-the-man-behind-gtd/"/>
    <updated>2005-10-14T07:26:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/10/14/interview-with-the-man-behind-gtd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Guardian has a <a href="http://technology.guardian.co.uk/businesssense/story/0,16568,1580180,00.html">very nice interview with David Allen</a>, the guy behind GTD. GTD stands for &lt;I&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/I&gt; and I <a href="http://blog.thylmann.net/2005/10/kinkless_gtd.html">posted</a> about it recently in terms of starting to use <a href="http://kinkless.com/articles/category/kgtd/">Kinless GTD</a>. The interview is a good introduction to GTD actually.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kinkless GTD]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/10/13/kinkless-gtd/"/>
    <updated>2005-10-13T14:06:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2005/10/13/kinkless-gtd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found the <a href="http://kinkless.com/articles/category/kgtd/">Kinkless GTD System</a> via <a href="http://www.43folders.com/2005/10/04/review-kinkless-gtd-for-automated-elegant-os-x-task-management/">this post</a> on 43 Folders and it does kick major ass. I was trying to find something similar for a long time, something that allows me to manage my tasks in an easy way and giving me a good overview about what happens next and what is waiting, keeping your head clear. If you have OmniOutliner Pro, try it out, otherwise download a trial or just buy the damn thing. :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Traffic on OUBS Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/10/26/traffic-on-oubs-blog/"/>
    <updated>2004-10-26T18:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/10/26/traffic-on-oubs-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I just signed up at <a href="http://www.statcounter.com/">Statcounter.com</a> I got some interesting stats. One would be from which ISPs the last 100 people came from, which gets especially interesting for the <a href="http://owt.typepad.com/oubs/">OUBS Blog</a> as the list includes some very nice universities. I might have to think about allowing some ads from people that want to connect to those people.</p>

<ol>
<li>British Library - UK</li>
<li>University Of Lincolnshire And Humberside, Sheffield, England, United Kingdom</li>
<li>University Of Central England In Birmingham, Reading, England, United Kingdom</li>
<li>Liverpool John Moores University, Liverpool, England, United Kingdom</li>
<li>University Of Phoenix, Phoenix, Arizona, United States</li>
<li>University Of Abertay Dundee, Dundee, Scotland, United Kingdom</li>
<li>University Of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota, United States</li>
<li>University Of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California, United States</li>
<li>Letterkenny Institute Of Technology, Letterkenny, Donegal, Ireland</li>
<li>Liverpool Institute Of Higer Education, Liverpool, England, United Kingdom</li>
<li>Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio, United States</li>
</ol>


<p>Not a bad list really I have to say and I presume some more people who study or have studied surf from home or from places where I didn't know where they came from.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wikipedia heals in 5 minutes]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/09/11/wikipedia-heals-in-5-minutes/"/>
    <updated>2004-09-11T08:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/09/11/wikipedia-heals-in-5-minutes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are still in doubt that Wikipedia, a Wiki that everyone out there can edit and change around, can work, I suggest you check out Joi's post entitled &lt;a title=&quot;Wikipedia heals in 5 minutes&quot; href=&quot;http://joi.ito.com/archives/2004/09/08/wikipedia_heals_in_5_minutes.html&quot;&gt;Wikipedia heals in 5 minutes&lt;/a&gt;. It links to a study (with an amazing graph by the way) from IBM about History Flow visualisation as they call it. What they did was analyse how long it takes for a deleted or greatly changed page in Wikipedia to be reactivated with the original correct one. The average is 5 minutes!!! Either you take it up, or you go back into your control world.</p>

<p>To quote General Shinseki: &quot;&lt;I&gt;If you don't like changge, you're going to like irrelevance even less.&lt;/I&gt;&quot;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Studies Week]]></title>
    <link href="http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/03/17/studies-week/"/>
    <updated>2004-03-17T08:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://thylmann.net/blog/2004/03/17/studies-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This seems to be studies week. I just put my summaries of <a href="http://owt.typepad.com/oubs/2004/03/project_apprais.html">Project Appraisal</a> and <a href="http://owt.typepad.com/oubs/2004/03/company_apprais.html">Company Appraisal</a> online on the <a href="http://owt.typepad.com/oubs/">OUBS Blog</a> in the last two days and to finish this off I just registered for a new course at the <a href="http://oubs.open.ac.uk/">OUBS</a>. This one is entitled &lt;i&gt;Creativity, Innovation and Change&lt;/i&gt; and will likely be both relaxing in relation to the current Finance course and a huge amount of fun. From what I hear it includes lots of different things to make up perfect teams, brainstorming, handling change, lots of interesting little tidbits. With the residential school on this one you are more or less asked to not stick with your group but to wonder arround, leave at any time, change groups, look at something else, ... wonder freely in a sense. Free your mind. I just hope that I will not free my mind up too much with this ;) We will see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
